[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Out of the following countries, which country has adopted the standard gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) England",
            "b) India",
            "c) Australia",
            "d) Pakistan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most of the European countries have adopted the standard gauge. England was the first country to adopt this gauge. It was previously known as Stephenson gauge. The size of the standard gauge is 1435mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The unit of rail gauge is expressed in terms of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time",
            "b) Length",
            "c) Velocity",
            "d) No unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gauge can be defined as the distance between inner sides of the rails. Therefore, it has a unit of length and generally expressed in mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which type of gauge is widely used across the world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metre gauge",
            "b) Broad gauge",
            "c) Standard gauge",
            "d) Cape gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Standard gauge line covers the most distance across the world. It covers approximately 60% of the total rail length in the world. Most of the high speed lines adopt this gauge size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "The size of cape gauge is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 mm",
            "b) 1067 mm",
            "c) 1435 mm",
            "d) 1676 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cape gauge which is widely used in Japan, Australia and New Zealand has a size of 1067 mm. The sizes of metre gauge, standard gauge and broad gauge are 1000 mm, 1435 mm and 1676 mm respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "The narrow gauge is more useful in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mountainous and hilly regions",
            "b) Plain areas",
            "c) Desert region",
            "d) Not useful"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The narrow gauge is superior to broad gauge in hilly regions as the cost of construction is reduced significantly. Also, narrow gauge allows small radius curves to be constructed easily.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What is the effect of increasing the gauge distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases the stability of the train",
            "b) Decreases the stability of the train",
            "c) Decreases the cost of construction",
            "d) Decreases the speed of the train"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A broader gauge increases the speed and stability of the train. The cost of construction is also increased.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Which of the following are types of gauges present in Indian railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Broad gauge, metre gauge and 2 narrow gauges",
            "b) Metre gauge, narrow gauge and 2 broad gauges",
            "c) Standard gauge, metre gauge and narrow gauge",
            "d) Broad gauge, standard gauge and metre gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 4 different types of gauges in Indian railways namely: broad gauge, meter gauge and 2 narrow gauges. The sizes of these gauges are: Broad gauge – 1676 mm, Metre gauge – 1000 mm, Narrow gauge – 762 mm and Narrow gauge – 610 mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Given below is the type of gauges used in India along with their size. Which one of the following is incorrectly matched?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Broad gauge – 1435 mm",
            "b) Metre gauge – 1000 mm",
            "c) Narrow gauge – 762 mm",
            "d) Narrow gauge – 610 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The broad gauge in India is of 1676 mm size. The size 1435 mm is of standard gauge which is widely used across the world. The broad gauge line in India covers approximately 64000 kilometers as of the year 2019.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Why did the Indian government introduce metre gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To reduce the cost of construction",
            "b) To provide stability to the rails",
            "c) To increase the speed of the train",
            "d) To improve the efficiency of the rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Indian government wanted to reduce the cost of construction of the railways. So, it introduced metre gauge of 1000 mm. The metre gauge line in India covers approximately 3200 kilometers distance as of 2019. “Nilgiri Mountain Railways” is one of the few metre gauge lines currently operating in India. It is also recognized as a World Heritage Site by UNESCO.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Metros and monorails in India use ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Broad gauge",
            "b) Metre gauge",
            "c) Standard gauge",
            "d) Narrow gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The metros and monorails in India use standard gauge of 1435 mm. Both metros and monorails are not owned by the Indian Railways. Apart from these, even the “Kolkata Tram System” uses the standard gauge line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "India’s first passenger train from BoriBunder (Mumbai) to Thane was run on which gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard gauge",
            "b) Broad gauge",
            "c) Narrow gauge",
            "d) Metre gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On 16th April 1853, India’s first passenger train ran from BoriBunderto Thane on broad gauge track. It carried 400 passengers and covered a distance of 34 km. It consisted of 14 carriages and was hauled by 3 steam locomotives.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Broad gauge line covers ____ % of total track length in India.",
        "Options": [
            "a) More than 90%",
            "b) 85 to 90%",
            "c) 80 to 85%",
            "d) Less than 80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Broad gauge is the most predominant gauge used in India. It covers a length of approximately 92% of the total rail route in India. The Indian Railways has decided to convert all the existing lines to broad gauge as part of “Project Unigauge”.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Which of the following railways has narrow gauge and is still operational?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Assam Bengal Railway",
            "b) Satpura Railway",
            "c) Darjeeling Himalayan Railway",
            "d) Bikaner State Railway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Darjeeling Himalayan Railway runs on narrow gauge and is still operational. It has been declared by UNESCO as a World Heritage Site. Satpura Railway, Assam Bengal Railway and Bikaner State railway have been recently converted from narrow gauge to broad gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Recently, India launched its first engineless semi-high speed train running on broad gauge. What was the name of the train?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Train 16",
            "b) Train 17",
            "c) Train 18",
            "d) Train 19"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. In 2017, the Indian Railways took a decision to convert all the metre gauge lines to broad gauge. However in 2018, a meeting was held and it was decided to preserve five metre gauge lines so as to attract more tourists.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "On whose recommendation the broad gauge was introduced in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mountbatten recommendation",
            "b) Warren Hastings recommendation",
            "c) W. Simms recommendation",
            "d) Dalhousie recommendation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Train 18 also known as “Vande Bharat Express” is India’s first engineless and semi-high speed train. It runs on broad gauge line and has speed of approximately 180 km/hour. It has been named as Train 18 as it took nearly 18 months for its completion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor influencing the choice of gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost of construction",
            "b) Volume of traffic",
            "c) Topography of the area",
            "d) Weather conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors affecting the choice of gauge in a particular area are: Cost of construction; Volume of traffic; Topography and geographical features; Future development prospects in that area and speed required. Weather in particular does not affect the choice of gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Which of the following is recommended while choosing a gauge in a particular country?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing a uniform gauge throughout the country",
            "b) Providing two types of gauge in a country",
            "c) Providing three types of gauge in a country",
            "d) Providing more than three types of gauge in a country"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A uniform gauge (i.e. only one type of gauge) should be provided throughout the country. This would enable smooth and efficient operation of the trains. Providing different gauges within the same country would cause connectivity problems.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "How is speed of the train related to the gauge distance provided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly proportional",
            "b) Inversely proportional",
            "c) Not related to the gauge distance provided",
            "d) Varies according to the topography of the place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A wider gauge has more capacity to withstand higher speed than a narrow gauge. Therefore, more the gauge distance more is the speed of the train.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "As per Indian Railways, the broad gauge has been classified into _____ groups based on _____ criteria.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Four, speed",
            "b) Five, terrain",
            "c) Four, terrain",
            "d) Five, speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False. A broad gauge can handle more traffic as it can carry larger wagons and coaches. Therefore, if traffic intensity increases in the narrow gauge then it needs to be converted to a wider gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Identify the correct relation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wheel diameter = 0.25 times gauge distance",
            "b) Wheel diameter = gauge distance",
            "c) Wheel diameter = 0.75 times gauge distance",
            "d) Wheel diameter = 1.5 times gauge distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The broad gauge has been classified into five different groups based on the speed of the train. The different groups are: Group A; Group B; Group C; Group D Special and Group E Special lines.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "If the width of the gauge is increased, which of the following cost is increased significantly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost of construction",
            "b) Cost of acquiring land",
            "c) Cost of rolling stock",
            "d) Cost of signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The wheel diameter is approximately taken as 0.75 times the gauge distance. This would help in smooth functioning of the wheels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "A new rail line needs to be constructed in a sparsely populated town. Which type of gauge can be recommended?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Broad gauge",
            "b) Standard gauge",
            "c) Narrow gauge",
            "d) Meter gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cost of acquiring land increases the most when the width of gauge is increased. Whereas the cost of construction increases slightly and cost of rolling stock is independent of the gauge provided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Metre gauge track routes in India can be classified as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) P-route, Q-route and R-route",
            "b) Q-route, R-route and S-route",
            "c) R-route, S-route and T-route",
            "d) S-route, T-route and U-route"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A narrow gauge can be used to construct a new line in a sparsely populated town. By using the narrow gauge, cost can be saved significantly. The cost of acquiring the land will be reduced significantly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "The operating cost per tonne per km _______ with increase in gauge width.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Independent",
            "c) Increases",
            "d) Neither increase nor decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The metre gauge track routes in India are classified into three categories based on speed and traffic density. These categories are: Q-route, R-route (which is subdivided into R-1, R-2 and R-3 routes) and S-route.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "The problems caused by change of gauge is popularly known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Break of gauge",
            "b) Rupture of gauge",
            "c) Separation of gauge",
            "d) Division of gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The problem caused by change of gauge is popularly known as “Break of gauge”.  A break of gauge is encountered when one gauge meets a different type of gauge at a place. For example: When a broad gauge line meets a metre gauge line at a place, it is called Break of gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "What problems do passengers face due to change of gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay in reaching their destination and inconvenience caused due to change of train",
            "b) Increase in ticket fares",
            "c) Danger of encountering accident during travel",
            "d) Loss of baggage during travel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A passenger can face a lot of problems due to change of gauge like delay in reaching their destination and inconvenience due to change of train (which includes transporting luggage to the other train, finding seats in the next train).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Widening an existing gauge involves _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Light engineering works",
            "b) Heavy engineering works",
            "c) Medium engineering works",
            "d) Very light engineering works"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To widen an existing gauge, it requires heavy civil engineering works such as widening of tunnels and bridges; replacing the tracks and old rolling stocks. During the gauge widening process, the line needs to be closed temporarily and hence this causes operational problems.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which of the following is/are problems caused due to trans-shipment of goods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Causes damage to goods only",
            "b) Causes both damage to goods and delay in delivering goods to their destination",
            "c) Causes delay in delivering goods to their destinationonly",
            "d) Causes no problems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Whenever a change of gauge is encountered, trans-shipment of goods needs to be done. During this process, damage of goods can take place and there will be delay in delivering these goods. Therefore, a change of gauge should also be avoided in goods transportation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a possible solution for change of gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Installation of check rails",
            "b) Installation of guard rails",
            "c) Installation of dual gauge",
            "d) Installation of dial gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. A country can face unbalanced economic growth due to presence of more than one gauge. Industries will face problems in receiving raw materials and delivering their goods. This will hamper the progress of industries and hence the growth of economy of any country.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which country was benefitted by the change of gauge problems in World War 2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Russia",
            "b) Germany",
            "c) Australia",
            "d) Poland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A dual gauge rail is the one which allows trains of different gauges to pass without stoppage. It is also known as the mixed gauge rail. In order to resolve the break of gauge problem, dual gauge track can be installed permanently. It can also be installed temporarily till conversion of gauge takes place.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which country uses “Automatic Gauge Changeover” system to overcome the change of gauge problems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) India",
            "b) Australia",
            "c) England",
            "d) Spain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Russia chose a gauge of 1520 mm rather than the conventional gauge size of 1435 mm. The choice benefitted them largely as it saved Moscow from being seized completely by Hitler in 1941. The German army transported most of its men and supplies through train. But when they reached Russia, they had to change the gauge of all the tracks. This slow process helped Russia in avoiding the defeat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "If there is more than one type of gauge present in a rail route, the journey time ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) Depends on the climate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Spain has currently three types of gauges namely: Iberian gauge (1668 mm), Standard gauge (1435 mm) and Metre gauge (1000 mm). To overcome the problems faced due to change of gauge, it uses “Automatic Gauge Changeover” system. In this system, the train passes through fixed gauge installations while the train wheels are altered. During this process, the train moves at a very low speed of 15 km/hour.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which five year plan did the Government of India introduce “Project Unigauge”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1985 to 1990",
            "b) 1992 to 1997",
            "c) 1997 to 2002",
            "d) 2002 to 2007"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the eighth five year plan (1992 to 1997), the Government of India introduced the plan of Indian Railways to convert 6000 km of metre gauge lines to broad gauge. This started the largest project of Indian Railways, i.e. “Project Unigauge”.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which line was first converted to broad gauge as a part of Project Unigauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lumding to Silchar",
            "b) Guwahati to Lumding",
            "c) Silchar to Jiribam",
            "d) Badarpur to Baraigram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On July 3 1992, the Prime Minister of India, P.V. NarsimhaRao launched the conversion of Guwahati to Lumding rail line. This marked the inauguration of Project Unigauge in India. This line conversion was eventually completed in January 1994.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Why did Indian Railways convert all the rail lines to broad gauge instead of standard gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Broad gauge lines have less maintenance and operating cost as compared to standard gauge lines",
            "b) Almost 50% of the rail lines in India were of broad gauge in the year 1992",
            "c) Broad gauge gives more stability to the wheels than Standard gauge",
            "d) Broad gauge offers more speed to the train than Standard gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the year 1992 (when the Project Unigauge started), almost 50% of the Indian rail lines were of broad gauge, 43% of metre gauge and remaining 7% of narrow gauge. Adopting a different gauge apart from these would mean converting all the existing lines. This was economically impossible to achieve. So, broad gauge was chosen which meant converting only metre and narrow gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "What was the disadvantage of choosing broad gauge for Project Unigauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non access to readily available rolling stock and poor technological development",
            "b) Costlier in the long run",
            "c) Poor carrying capacity and handled less traffic",
            "d) Speed of the train was reduced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As the Standard gauge was the most widely used gauge in the world, most of the technological development was done on it. If India had chosen this gauge, it would have easy access to readily available rolling stock and track. Choosing broad gauge made India design its own locomotives and rolling stock.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which of the following rail line is not a part of the “Mountain Railways of India”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Darjeeling Himalayan Railway",
            "b) Nilgiri Mountain Railway",
            "c) Kalka – Shimla Railway",
            "d) Lumding – Badarpur Railway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The “Mountain Railways of India” consists of three rail lines namely: Darjeeling Himalayan Railway, Nilgiri Mountain Railway and Kalka – Shimla Railway. These lines are narrow gauge and are not included in the Project Unigauge. They are included in the UNESCO World Heritage sites.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following narrow gauge line is not included in Project Unigauge and is on the “tentative list” of UNESCO World Heritage Site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Matheran Hill Railway",
            "b) Nilgiri Mountain Railway",
            "c) Ahmedabad – Ranuj Railway",
            "d) Darjeeling Himalayan Railway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Matheran Hill Railway is a narrow gauge line of 610 mm size in the state of Maharashtra. This will not be converted to broad gauge line. It has been preserved to increase the tourism in the country. It is also on the “tentative list” of UNESCO World Heritage site. This railway connects Neral in Mumbai to Matheran in the Western Ghats.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "The Lucknow – Sitapur rail line in Uttar Pradesh was converted to broad gauge (as part of Project Unigauge) in which year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2017",
            "b) 2016",
            "c) 2019",
            "d) 2014"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The conversion of 90 km stretch of Lucknow – Sitapur rail line to broad gauge was completed in January, 2019. The former Minister of State for Railways, ManojSinha inaugurated the new rail line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Suppose India had decided to convert all rail lines to standard gauge in “Project Unigauge”. What benefits it would have served?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in project completion time",
            "b) Reduction in project cost",
            "c) Better connectivity of rail lines with other countries",
            "d) Increase in speed of train"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If India adopted Standard gauge for all its rail lines, then it would help in better connectivity with other countries through rail. Having a better connection through rail with other countries would help in easy transportation of goods and passengers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "If a uniform gauge is chosen throughout the country, the transport bottlenecks will ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remain same",
            "d) Depends on speed of train"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. Due to low population of small towns and villages, narrow or metre gauge lines were used in these areas to save cost. But this largely affected their connectivity to other towns or cities (i.e. they encountered “Break of Gauge” problems). The unigauge policy of converting all rail lines to broad gauge will help solve this problem of small towns.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "What does the term “Loading Gauge” refer to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum length of rail vehicle",
            "b) Maximum height and width of rail vehicle",
            "c) Maximum weight of rail vehicle",
            "d) Minimum height and width of rail vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term “loading Gauge” refers to the maximum height and width of the rail vehicle. This ensures safe passage of trains through tunnels, bridges, platforms, etc. Therefore, a design of railway vehicle is made keeping in mind the limiting values of loading gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "The term “Rolling Stock” in Railways includes ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Locomotives, coaches and wagons",
            "b) Sleepers, tracks and gauges",
            "c) Wheels and sleepers",
            "d) Tracks and platforms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Railways terminology, the term “Rolling Stock” includes locomotives, coaches and wagons or any vehicle that runs on rail tracks. It can include both powered and unpowered vehicles. The rolling stock can act as an engine (for eg. locomotive) or can be used to carry passengers (for eg. coaches) or can be used to carry goods (for eg. wagon).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "As per the Indian Railways, the maximum height and maximum width of the rolling stock for Broad Gauge (BG) is _____ mm and _____ mm respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3455 mm and 2745 mm",
            "b) 4140 mm and 3250 mm",
            "c) 4830 mm and 3600 mm",
            "d) 3455 mm and 3250 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to the Indian Railways, the maximum height and maximum width of rolling stock for Broad Gauge (BG) is 4140 mm and 3250 mm respectively and for Metre Gauge (MG), the values are 3455 mm and 2745 mm. These dimensions should be strictly followed and maintained while designing the rolling stocks for Indian Railways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "What does a construction gauge mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loading gauge + extra clearance",
            "b) Another name of loading gauge",
            "c) Maximum length of the rolling stock",
            "d) Loading gauge – extra clearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A construction gauge refers to the loading gauge plus the extra clearance or necessary clearance given to the loading gauge so that the train can pass safely at the same speed without any stoppage. Therefore, construction gauge = loading gauge + extra clearance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "The bridges and tunnels are built with respect to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loading gauge",
            "b) Narrow gauge",
            "c) Construction gauge",
            "d) Cape gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A rolling stock is built in accordance to the loading gauge. This rolling stock should pass through bridges and tunnels without any collision or contact. Therefore, an extra clearance in addition to loading gauge is used while designing the bridges and tunnels. This is known as construction gauge. Hence, the bridges and tunnels are built with respect to the construction gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "Which locomotive in India is listed in “Guinness Book of World Records” for being the oldest operational steam locomotive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fairy Queen",
            "b) DHR 778",
            "c) Indian locomotive class SG",
            "d) Nilgiri Mountain Railway X class"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The East Indian Railway Nr. 22, popularly known as the “Fairy Queen” is the oldest steam locomotive which is still operational and is listed in the “Guinness Book of World Records”. It was built in the year 1855. It runs between New Delhi to Alwar.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "What does alignment of a railway track mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direction and position of the centerline of track in horizontal plane only",
            "b) Direction and position @ 50mm distance on either side of centerline of track",
            "c) Direction and position of the centerline of track in both horizontal and vertical planes",
            "d) Direction and position of the centerline of track in vertical plane only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In railway terminology, “Alignment” means the direction and position of the centerline of the railway track with respect to both horizontal and vertical planes. A proper alignment of the track will ensure the safety and comfort of the passengers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of vertical alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Level track",
            "b) Gradient",
            "c) Vertical curve",
            "d) Gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The vertical alignment of a railway track refers to the direction and position it follows in the vertical plane. This includes gradient, level track and vertical curve. Whereas the horizontal alignment of a railway track refers to the direction and position it follows in the plan.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "How is accuracy of the rail alignment related to the operating speed of the train?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inversely proportional",
            "b) Directly proportional",
            "c) No relation exists",
            "d) Varies from place to place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: False. Once a railway track is constructed, it is very difficult to change its alignment. This is because of the difficulty in acquiring more land and reconstructing the already existing costly structures. Therefore, changing the alignment will take more time and prove costly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "The alignment survey of the Mumbai-Ahmedabad High Speed Corridor was done by which agency?",
        "Options": [
            "a) JICA",
            "b) SNCF",
            "c) Indian Railways",
            "d) RITES"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: More the accuracy of the rail alignment more will be the operating speed of the train. Improper alignment (either in horizontal plane or vertical plane) will reduce the speed of train and cause discomfort to the passengers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Which of the following software cannot be used to design a railway track alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open Rail Designer",
            "b) Trimble Quantm",
            "c) Ferrovia",
            "d) Primavera"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Mumbai-Ahmedabad High Speed Corridor will be India’s first high speed rail line when completed. The project is scheduled to be completed by August, 2022. Japanese International Cooperation Agency (JICA) did the alignment survey and also researched about the technology to be used in the project.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a basic requirement of ideal alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shortest possible route",
            "b) Comfort of the passengers",
            "c) Maximum operational expenses",
            "d) Safety of the passengers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An ideal alignment of a railway track should have the shortest possible route and should be economically feasible. It should have minimum operational expenses and low cost of maintenance. It should provide safety and comfort to the passengers and should be aesthetically pleasing to the eyes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "The maintenance cost of the rail line can be decreased by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing steep gradients",
            "b) Avoiding steep gradients",
            "c) Providing sharp turns",
            "d) Avoiding mild gradients"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maintenance cost of a new rail line can be reduced significantly if we avoid steep gradients and sharp turns. This is because the rails and rolling stock undergoes heavy wear and tear when it encounters a steep gradient or a sharp turn.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Cut and fill of earthwork is performed while constructing a new rail line on undulating surface. Which of the following condition should be maintained so that construction cost is minimized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quantity of cut = Quantity of fill",
            "b) Construction cost is independent of quantity of cut and fill",
            "c) Quantity of cut > Quantity of fill",
            "d) Quantity of cut < Quantity of fill"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: True. A rail journey is usually of a long duration. It should be aesthetically pleasing to the passengers. This can be achieved by passing the rail alignment through natural surroundings and avoiding views of borrow pits.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "In railways terminology, what do obligatory points mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Points through which the railway line must pass",
            "b) Points through which the railway line should not pass",
            "c) Points where railway signals must be placed",
            "d) Points where rail crossings are provided"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In railways terminology, obligatory points are the points through which the rail line must pass due to political or commercial reasons and also taking into consideration the technical aspects. These may include major towns and cities, major bridges, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Obligatory points are also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Controlling points",
            "b) Saddle points",
            "c) Rolling points",
            "d) Important points"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Obligatory points are also known as controlling points. For a good alignment, shortest possible route should be chosen but it should also pass through intermediate major cities which are of commercial or political importance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "If the gradient exceeds the ruling gradient, which technique much be adopted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control technique",
            "b) Development technique",
            "c) Management technique",
            "d) Ruling technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally, in case of mountainous terrain the gradient to be provided exceeds the ruling gradient. In order to avoid this, development technique is adopted in which the length of the rail line is increased, thereby decreasing the gradient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which of the following method of rail alignment is preferred in case of steep side slopes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zigzag line method",
            "b) Switch back method",
            "c) Spiral method",
            "d) Cubic method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If a steep side slope is present, switch back method of rail alignment is used. In this method, the direction of the train route is reversed by providing a switch. The train has to necessarily stop and change direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "The spiral method, also known as ________ method is used in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete loop; narrow valley",
            "b) Incomplete loop; flat terrain",
            "c) Complete loop; flat terrain",
            "d) Incomplete loop; narrow valley"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The figure depicts the zigzag line method of alignment. It is used when mountainous terrain is encountered. In this method, the railway line passes in a zigzag manner and it turns approximately 180 degree (like a horseshoe pattern) to gain the required height.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "The alignment of a rail line should pass through a place that faces ______ the direction of wind.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Towards",
            "b) Away from",
            "c) Towards or away from",
            "d) At an angle of 30 degree from"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The spiral method or complete loop method of alignment is used in a narrow valley, especially where a small bridge has been constructed. A railway line completes a loop and crossed itself at a higher level.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "At what angle should a railway line cross a road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90°",
            "b) 30°",
            "c) 60°",
            "d) 45°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rail line alignment should be such that it passes through a place that faces away from the direction of wind. In the case of hot climate region, it can pass through sand dunes which face away from the direction of the wind. In the case of cold climate regions, it can pass through sides of hills that face away from the direction of wind.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "What formula can be used to calculate the “Maximum Annual Return” of a rail alignment? (Given: R = Gross revenue earned by railway line; E = Annual running expenses).",
        "Options": [
            "a) R + E",
            "b) R – E",
            "c) R / E",
            "d) E / R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A railway line should always cross a road at 90° angle, i.e. they should be perpendicular to each other. This is done so that the passing train is clearly visible to the road passengers, thus avoiding accidents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "A railway line passes through a terrain which crosses watershed areas of two or more streams. Which type of alignment can be preferred?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plane alignment",
            "b) Mountain alignment",
            "c) Cross country alignment",
            "d) Valley alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum annual returns (M) can be calculated by the formula: M = R – E\nFor a particular rail line, various alternative alignments are considered. The alignment with the maximum annual return is chosen and finalized.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "What type of gauges are generally used for mountain railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Narrow gauges",
            "b) Broad gauges",
            "c) Metre gauges",
            "d) Cape gauges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Laying of wide gauges is extremely challenging in mountainous regions. This is due to the presence of very steep slopes and difficult excavation processes. Thus narrow gauges (762mm or 610mm) are used in mountain railways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Which of the following alignments is least preferred in case of mountain railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spiral",
            "b) Zigzag",
            "c) Switch-back",
            "d) Straight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adaption of straight alignment for mountain regions is less preferred because it will lead to a very steep track. This will be difficult for travelling and construction. Thus for easy attainment of heights spiral, zigzag or switch-back alignments are followed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "The tracks which have gradient greater than or equal to 3% are considered as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sharp tracks",
            "b) Mountain tracks",
            "c) Zigzag tracks",
            "d) High speed tracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Adaption of narrow gauges lead to less excavation activities and less requirement of track material. This leads to reduction in total cost of construction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Up to what value the curvatures are generally adopted in mountain railway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35°",
            "b) 40°",
            "c) 50°",
            "d) 45°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mountain tracks require very steep gradients because vertical distance to be travelled is more than usual. Thus they require gradient of 3% or more.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "How is Rack railway system different from normal railway system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is wider",
            "b) It has an extra toothed rail",
            "c) Extra friction is provided in the two rails",
            "d) They are made of different materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Huge amount of energy is required to pull the wagons in case of a slope steeper than 3%. If the hauling capacity of the train is not enough, the train may slide down the track.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is the position of the toothed rail in Rack rail system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the middle of the two rails",
            "b) Connected with one of the rails",
            "c) At a distance of 500mm from one rail",
            "d) Can be placed anywhere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answers: b\nExplanation: The rack railway system has a toothed rail in addition with the two usual rails. This creates an interlocking system between toothed rail and wheel of the locomotive.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "What type of additional wheels are used for locomotives in Rack railway system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toothed pinion wheels",
            "b) Coned wheels",
            "c) High density wheels",
            "d) No change in wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The toothed rail is provided centrally in between the two regular rails. Placing of rail anywhere else can reduce precision. This will also lead to difficulty in manufacturing of toothed pinion wheels in locomotive.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "What is the most important strategic reason for the construction of a new railway line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase tourists",
            "b) To make movement of defence forces easier in case of emergency",
            "c) For creating jobs",
            "d) Because of absence of a railway line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of natural calamities like flood, earthquake or during threat of war, presence of a railway line is very important. It ensures fast movement of defence forces and relief material to the area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "How can we shorten the existing rail link between two points?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Construction of new railway line on shorter alignment",
            "b) Increasing the gauge size",
            "c) Increasing the capacity of locomotive",
            "d) It isn’t possible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate of development of an area increases after the construction of a new railway line. A new railway line connects the area to new market places and makes travelling faster. This increases the business and job opportunities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "What can be done to manage the increase in traffic between two points?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase the number of sleepers",
            "b) Changing the depth of ballast cushion",
            "c) Converting the single rail lines to double",
            "d) Changing the material of the rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A new alignment, shorter than the one already present can be selected between the two points. This makes construction economical and also reduces the time and fare of travel. This is how the existing rail link can be shortened.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a step taken by the Indian railways to ensure smooth flow of traffic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Converting all the metre gauge lines to broad gauge lines",
            "b) Converting all the metre gauge lines to narrow gauge lines",
            "c) Increasing the width of sleepers in track",
            "d) Using concrete for construction of sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We can deal with the increase in traffic by increasing the number of rail lines from one to two. This will allow multiple trains to travel simultaneously.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "What can be concluded after preliminary investigations for a new railway line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Whether the new railway line is required or not",
            "b) The topography of the ground",
            "c) The alignment of the rail line",
            "d) The number of sleepers required for the new track"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In preliminary investigations we study the trade and population of that area. The traffic density and statistical data of other trains operating on similar terrains is analysed. From this we can conclude whether the new train is required or not.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "What is the next step taken after the preliminary investigation of the rail line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laying of rail lines",
            "b) Formation of ballast",
            "c) Surveying",
            "d) Testing of rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In preliminary investigation the topography sheets and other maps of the area are studied. The properties of the railway line are decided by considering the scope of future development.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of survey conducted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preliminary survey",
            "b) Traffic survey",
            "c) Reconnaissance survey",
            "d) Transverse curve survey"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: After preliminary investigation it is important to know the gradients of the path on which rails are to be laid. The alignment, curves need to be calculated. For this purpose surveying is done after Preliminary investigation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "What type of conditions are studied in Traffic survey of an area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Topographical",
            "b) Traffic",
            "c) Environmental",
            "d) Political"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After preliminary investigation the first type of survey done is Traffic survey. This tells the traffic density which is to be carried by the locomotive. Various features of the rail line are proposed based on the results of the Traffic survey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a function of Traffic survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determination of best route for railway",
            "b) To determine the probable traffic the rail line will have to carry",
            "c) To decide the standard of Rail line",
            "d) To determine the curvature of the turns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Traffic surveys are done to estimate the traffic that the railway will carry. Based on that the standard of rail line and alignment is decided. It has nothing to do with the determination of curvature or gradient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "The team conducting survey must visit the state government, prominent businessmen, and Local bodies and then propose the suitable ______ of the new rail line.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost",
            "b) Alignment",
            "c) Length",
            "d) Traction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Traffic surveys are done in correspondence with Reconnaissance or Preliminary survey. This helps in knowing the technical feasibility and relative costs of different proposals. The best option can be selected after considering all these factors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "While doing Traffic survey of an area, information should be gathered on which topics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only on the existing traffic facilities",
            "b) Human resources and existing traffic facilities",
            "c) Only on the pattern of trade and commerce",
            "d) On existing traffic facilities, human resources and pattern of trade and commerce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The new line should be beneficial for all the trade centres, citizens and businessmen of that area. It should not impact the development of that area negatively. Thus the best alignment should be chosen after consulting the government, local bodies and other prominent people.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "What is the objective of Reconnaissance survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To make a contour map of the area.",
            "b) To determine the technical feasibility of proposal",
            "c) To determine rough cost of one or more alternatives to the new line",
            "d) To determine the technical feasibility as well as the best possible alternatives available"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reconnaissance survey is done to check if the execution of the work is possible technically and economically. It also includes a rough estimate of one or more alternatives available to the new line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "The Reconnaissance survey is done based on _____ and other already available data.",
        "Options": [
            "a) traffic flow of area",
            "b) estimated construction cost",
            "c) contoured survey maps",
            "d) population of that area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this survey contoured maps are studied and different alternatives to the new line are determined. It is generally done with the data which is readily available.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "What is the next step after the survey team studies the general topography of the country?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collection of field data",
            "b) Consulting government officials and local bodies",
            "c) Cost Estimation",
            "d) Laying down the rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Contoured maps of the area are studied to determine alternative alignments to the new line. Before starting its construction field data is collected by using various instruments. Based on this data the technical aspects of the new line are determined.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "What is the use of prismatic compass in survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To measure weight of an object",
            "b) To measure magnetic bearing of the alignment",
            "c) To view the physical features",
            "d) To determine magnetic lines of attraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnetic compass is used to determine the bearing of the alignment with respect to the north direction. Various technical aspects of the rail track are calculated based on the magnetic bearings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "What is the instrument ‘Abney level’ also called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Barometer",
            "b) Theodolite",
            "c) Clinometer",
            "d) Aneroid Barometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Abney level is also called as hand level or Clinometer. It is used in survey to measure gradients or angles of slopes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which are the instruments used for Reconnaissance survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prismatic compass, Binocular and Clinometer",
            "b) Abney level and Aneroid Barometer",
            "c) Only Prismatic compass is used",
            "d) Clinometer, Binocular, Pedometer, Aneroid Barometer and Prismatic compass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pedometer is used to get an idea of the distance travelled while walking. Binocular is used to view the physical features and Aneroid Barometer is used to find relative heights of points. Prismatic compass and Clinometer are used for calculating magnetic bearing and gradient of slopes respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Which of the following equipment is not a part of Modern Surveying Instruments and techniques?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infrared Beam",
            "b) Laser beam",
            "c) Chain and Tape",
            "d) Computers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chain and Tape were previously used for measurement. With advancement of technologies they are considered to be out dated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "What is the advantage of Modern Surveying Instruments and Techniques over old ones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are cheap",
            "b) They give very accurate results",
            "c) They are easy to operate",
            "d) They have high power consumption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Modern Techniques rely completely on digital instruments for surveying. This eliminates the possibility of human error, increases efficiency and gives more accurate results.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "What is the full form of EDM instruments used for modern surveying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronic Distance Measurement",
            "b) Electromagnetic Distance Measurement",
            "c) Electronic Diameter Measurement",
            "d) Elastic Deformation Meter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electronic Distance Measurement instruments are very advance and versatile. They can measure Horizontal and Vertical distances rapidly and efficiently.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "In Laser survey what is the replacement for invisible line of sight of ordinary survey instruments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bright Red beam of Laser",
            "b) Invisible beam of Laser",
            "c) Magnetic waves",
            "d) Sound Waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Laser beam has a property of low diversion. This is used for alignment purposes for the new rail line. It emits a bright red beam which hits the light sensitive cells on the target and distance between them is obtained.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "What major points should be included in the Project report for a Reconnaissance survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total cost estimate",
            "b) Whether it’s feasible to carry the project further or not",
            "c) Total cost estimate, feasibility of the project and Map of the area",
            "d) Total cost estimate and feasibility of the project"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A bright red beam is emitted from the laser which can travel large distances. The beam travels in perfectly straight line, thus chance of mistake is very less. This light amplification can measure distances up to 70km.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "What is the objective of Preliminary survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To estimate the cost of the proposed railway line",
            "b) To study the traffic flow",
            "c) To decide the alignment based on the trade links",
            "d) To choose proper gauge"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Preliminary survey is done to determine the cost of the rail line to be constructed. Traffic survey is done to study the traffic the train will carry and various alignments are analysed in Reconnaissance survey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "What is done to estimate the cost of the rail line to be constructed in Preliminary survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Instrumental examination of the route to be selected",
            "b) Study the topography with the help of maps",
            "c) Meeting with local bodies and prominent people",
            "d) Cost is estimated based on different lines of similar alignments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The survey team estimates the cost of the new line by calculations based on the readings of the instrumental survey. Based on the reports of Reconnaissance survey and Preliminary survey the railway administration then decides whether to construct the new line or not.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Why is Theodolite used for Preliminary survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For measuring magnetic bearings of alignments",
            "b) For traversing the centre line",
            "c) For pegging the centre line",
            "d) For both traversing and pegging the centre line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: With the help of theodolite horizontal and vertical angles can be measured. In field it is used for Traversing and pegging the centre line. Magnetic bearing is measured with the help of prismatic compass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "What is the use of Tacheometer in Preliminary survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For taking longitudinal and cross levels",
            "b) For plotting main features",
            "c) For pegging the centre line",
            "d) For getting details of various features"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For taking longitudinal and cross levels dumpy level is used. Plane table is used for getting details of various features and tacheometer is used for plotting main features.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not a part of the report prepared after Preliminary survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Characteristics of project area",
            "b) Route selection",
            "c) Standard of Construction",
            "d) Population projection and volume projection of Traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: While doing survey on site longitudinal and cross levelling is also done 200m on either side of the alignment. This is to ensure high accuracy of the contour maps.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "When is the Final Location survey done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) After the particular Railway line to be constructed is decided",
            "b) After the Traffic survey",
            "c) After Reconnaissance survey",
            "d) Immediately after the collection of Field data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Once the route of the new line to be constructed is decided, final location survey is done. It is done with the help of same instruments used in Preliminary survey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "What is the objective of Final location survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To study the contour maps",
            "b) To prepare working details",
            "c) To make accurate cost estimates",
            "d) To prepare working details and make accurate cost estimates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Final location survey is done to prepare the working details for site work and to make accurate cost estimates if required. Studying of Contour maps is a part of the Reconnaissance survey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "In Final location survey at which points Masonry pillars are built?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tangent point of curves",
            "b) At start and end of curves",
            "c) At tangent points and along the centre line",
            "d) Along the centre line of curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Final location survey must be precise and free of errors. Theodolite must be used in Final location survey for traversing the alignment, but it may not be used in case of Preliminary survey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which points should be considered while selecting the best alignment in Final location survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Correct obligatory points and minimum cost of construction",
            "b) Ease and minimum cost of construction",
            "c) Correct obligatory points and potential for high speeds",
            "d) Ease and minimum cost of construction, correct obligatory points and potential for high speeds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Masonry pillars are built alongside the railway track in Final location survey. They are built at tangent points of curves and also along the centre line at intervals of 500m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "In Characteristics of the Project Areas the geographical features of the country are given. These features do not affect the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) alignment of the rail line",
            "b) future prospects of proposed line",
            "c) cost of construction",
            "d) hauling capacity of the train"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The best alignment should be chosen for construction of the new railway line. The alignment chosen must satisfy criteria like potential for high speeds, ease, minimum cost of construction and correct obligatory points. The cost of maintenance should be minimum and scope of future expansion should be present.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "What does Category of a line indicates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum speed potential of the line",
            "b) Maximum axel load",
            "c) Loading standard of the bridges",
            "d) Maximum speed potential, axel load and loading standard of the bridges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The geographical features which affect the alignment, cost of construction, stability of line and future prospects of proposed line are given in the Project report. The hauling capacity of the train does not depend on the path to be travelled.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "The Permanent way section of the report does not give details about which of the following aspects?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The rail section adopted",
            "b) The depth of the Ballast cushion",
            "c) Whether or not to weld the rails",
            "d) Type and density of sleepers provided"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The category of line is a part of the standard of construction of the line. It tells the reason for choosing a particular line based on the maximum speed potential, axel load and loading standard of the bridges.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Which segment in the project report provides information and data related to the different routes that were examined for construction of the new rail line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Route selection",
            "b) Signalling and Telecommunication",
            "c) Other details",
            "d) Ruling gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The type and depth of ballast cushion provided is not included in the permanent way section. It only tells about the rail section adopted, type and density of sleepers and whether rails should be welded or not.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "What are the other details provided in the segment ‘Standard of construction’?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Road crossings and station machinery",
            "b) Only the station machinery",
            "c) Residential accommodation",
            "d) Road crossings, station machinery and residential accommodation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Route selection segment gives details about various routes that were examined. It also tells the factors that were considered while selecting the best alignment and why the specific alignment was chosen above the rest.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Which section focuses on the problems that might be encountered, identifying areas requiring special attention and providing knowledge and information for finding solutions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Project Engineering",
            "b) Route selection",
            "c) Signalling and Telecommunication",
            "d) Estimation of cost and construction schedule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are different segments present in the Standard of construction which give details about various aspects like Traction, Ballast, Permanent way etc. There are other miscellaneous details provided like Road crossings, station machinery, residential accommodation, service, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which section comments on the availability of water for various construction activities and its appropriateness for consumption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Project Engineering",
            "b) Estimation and cost of construction",
            "c) Project Organisation",
            "d) Environmental Section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: This section gives data and information to the Project manager. This helps the administration to understand the project so that they can devise a method for proper management and execution of the project.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "What is the order of arrangement of documents in the Report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Index, Report, Covering note",
            "b) Covering note, Index, Report, List of drawings, Appendices",
            "c) Index, Covering note, Report, List of drawings, Appendices",
            "d) Covering note, Index, Report, Appendices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Project organisation deals with water availability and its fitness for drinking. It also comments on the Hygiene and health of the staff members and appropriate medical arrangements needed. It may also indicate the cost of such plans.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not included in the Appendices to the report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Historical and geographical aspects",
            "b) Route selection and project description",
            "c) Location report",
            "d) Rates for construction work"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the documents belonging to the Final Location survey report must be in the order of- Covering note, Index, Report, List of drawings, Appendices.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Which organization provides the maps for satellite imagery?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DROD",
            "b) ISRO",
            "c) BARC",
            "d) NHAI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Satellite imagery is used for surveying of difficult terrains. It provides a bird’s eye view of the area and the maps are updated once a month.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "For which areas satellite imagery is most useful in the initial stages of planning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Where support data and existing map coverage are inadequate",
            "b) Where map coverage is insufficient and field evaluation is difficult",
            "c) Area with Insufficient support data and difficult field evaluation",
            "d) Area with Inadequate support data, existing map coverage and difficult field evaluation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Detailed analysis of the ground can be done with the help of satellite imagery and topographic maps. With the help of these the best corridor is chosen which satisfies all surveying prospects and can be further analysed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "The miniature details for the preliminary survey can be can be worked out with the help of contour maps, computer aids and ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) photogrammetric plotted sheets",
            "b) satellite images",
            "c) aerial photographs",
            "d) auto level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Satellite imagery is most useful in areas having challenging terrain where surveying is very difficult. It can also be very helpful in case of an area having insufficient map coverage and support data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "What is the first step involved in Construction of a New line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ballasting of track",
            "b) Land acquisition",
            "c) Earthwork and bridges",
            "d) Plate laying"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first step involved in construction of new lines is acquisition of Land. After that earthwork, bridges and laying of plate is done.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Where should one refer to for the procedure of acquisition of land with the help of member state government?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Land Acquisition act",
            "b) Land Surveying act",
            "c) Rules of Railway Board",
            "d) Indian Standard codes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For acquisition of land one should follow the rules, regulations and procedure as written in section 4 and 6 of the Land Acquisition act. In case of emergency land can be acquired by using special sections 9 and 17 of the act.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "What does the slide slope provided for the embankment depends upon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost of construction",
            "b) Traffic flow",
            "c) Nature of soil",
            "d) Rainfall intensity of that area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The land acquired should have scope for future expansions. It should be sufficient for construction of borrows, formation and pits. Thus even for the construction of a single line the land available must be sufficient for the construction of a double line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Why is the Formation of an embankment preferred over formation in a cutting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is economical",
            "b) It has good drainage properties",
            "c) It is easy to construct",
            "d) Less earthwork required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Slide slope is provided for easy drainage property and to reduce soil erosion. It depends on the Nature of soil of that area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "What is the objective of doing mechanical compaction after laying each layer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To obtain maximum moisture content",
            "b) To obtain minimum dry density",
            "c) To obtain maximum dry density at optimum moisture content",
            "d) To increase coarse grain content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The formation is made in an embankment or cutting depending on the contour and rail level of that area. As formation in embankment is higher than the ground level, it keeps the rail safe during floods and allows easy drainage of water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which curve is used to determine the economical lead of moving earth in the longitudinal direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass-haul curve",
            "b) Optimum moisture content curve",
            "c) Plasticity index curve",
            "d) Atterberg limits curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the earthwork to be stable it must have appropriate moisture content. More or less water content will affect its firmness. Thus a sheep foot roller is used for doing mechanical compaction so that maximum dry density can be obtained at optimum moisture content.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Why is the section where earthwork is to be donedivided into different zones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earthwork required is less",
            "b) For early execution of earthwork",
            "c) To provide different facilities to sections",
            "d) To increase traffic flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In an area where both embankment and cutting type of formation are present, the earth from cutting should be utilised for embankments up to an economical lead. This economical lead of moving earth in the longitudinal direction is determined by using Mass-haul curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "What are the factors on which the design of Bridges of railway are dependent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Topography of the country",
            "b) Type of stream to be covered",
            "c) Topography and Type of stream",
            "d) Topography, type of stream and Local bodies of the area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dividing earthwork into different zones makes the work very convenient. Each zone has a different Tender allotted which enables simultaneous progress of work in zones. Thus division of section in zones allows timely execution of earthwork.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a part of Plate laying or Track linking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laying sleepers",
            "b) Formation of embankment or cutting",
            "c) Laying rails",
            "d) Laying fastenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Bridge should be so designed that it should easily carry the load of the heaviest vehicle locomotive that will pass over it. The design of bridges like RCC, Steel, and PRC depend upon the topography of the area and the stream which lies in its path.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "In which method of Plate laying a temporary line is laid by side the of the proposed railway track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tram line method",
            "b) American method",
            "c) Telescopic method",
            "d) British method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The laying of rails, sleepers and fastenings is done after the construction of Formation. But construction of formation is not a part of Plate laying or Track linking.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "On what type of Terrain is the Tram line method most useful?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hilly terrain",
            "b) Rolling terrain",
            "c) Flat terrain",
            "d) Its suitable for all terrains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tram line method is useful in case of a Flat terrain. This is because laying of tram line on flat ground is convenient, cheaper and faster as compared to other terrains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "In Side method what is used for carrying track material on site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trucks travelling on a service road",
            "b) Trains just like in Tram line method",
            "c) With the help of cranes",
            "d) Humans carry the material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Side line method is slightly different than Tram line method. This is because it uses Trucks which travel on a service road parallel to the track for carrying track materials to the work site.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "For what type of banks, Borrow pits are provided only on one side of the track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High banks",
            "b) Low banks",
            "c) High and Medium banks",
            "d) Does not depend on type of banks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If land available is cheap, separate land should also be made available for Borrow pits. Borrow pits may be on one or both sides of the track for low banks and high or medium banks respectively. In case of costly land area, no Borrow pits are provided and earth is taken from neighbouring areas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Why are Service buildings required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For providing services for running the trains",
            "b) To maintain the tracks",
            "c) For residential purpose",
            "d) To make full use of land available"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Service buildings are required so that the staff can work there for smooth functioning of station and running of trains. These service buildings include Station master’s administrative centre, Telegraph office, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Which is the most widely used method for Track linking and Plate laying?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tram line method",
            "b) American method",
            "c) Telescopic method",
            "d) Side method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Telescopic method is extensively used in Indian Railways. In this method, material is unloaded after taking it to the base depot. The track is then laid and packed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Where is the first base depot for unloading of materials situated at?",
        "Options": [
            "a) End of existing line",
            "b) Start of new line",
            "c) Junction of existing line and new line to be constructed",
            "d) Anywhere based on the topography of the area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In telescopic method, for further laying of the track, material is carried up to the advanced rail head with the help of a Dip lorry. The track is then linked and packed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which special type of rail carrier is used for carrying of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anderson rail carrier",
            "b) Smith rail carrier",
            "c) Dip lorry",
            "d) Rail tongs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first depo is at the junction of the new line to be constructed and the existing line. Track material is carried up to the rail head from the depo with the help of a Dip lorry. Material gangs are then used to unload these materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "For which type of sleepers rail screws are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concrete sleepers",
            "b) Steel Sleepers",
            "c) Cast iron sleepers",
            "d) Wooden sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each rail weighs around 600kg and huge manpower is required for handling them. Consequently a special type of rail carrier is used. This is the Anderson rail carrier which can easily carry rails with lesser strain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Expansion gap between rails is provided with the help of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) rail screws",
            "b) steel liners or shims",
            "c) bolts",
            "d) fastenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For fixing rails to wooden sleepers rail screws are used. A key is used in case of steel sleeper. Bearing plates are provided according to need and track specifications.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Which among the following is generally used for Ballasting of tacks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ballast trains",
            "b) Ballast trains and manual methods",
            "c) Human efforts",
            "d) Dip lorry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adequate gaps are left between two rails which are called as expansion gaps. Steel liners or shims of appropriate thickness are used for providing these gaps.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "What measure is taken in case of curves to account for the centrifugal force acting on the train?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superelevation is provided",
            "b) Rack rail is provided",
            "c) Different sleepers are used",
            "d) Formation is different"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The outer edge of the track is raised with respect to the inner edge in case of a curve. This is called as superelevation, which counters the effect of the centrifugal force acting on the train.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Why the railway track is made resilient and elastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To make it economic",
            "b) So that it absorbs shocks",
            "c) It can be adjusted easily",
            "d) Easy fixing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The trains exert a lot of pressure on the tracks. They are made elastic and robust so that they can absorb these shocks and vibrations easily.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a requirement of a good track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good lateral strength",
            "b) Good drainage property",
            "c) Aesthetic appearance",
            "d) Low cost and maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The track experiences various temperature changes and must have good lateral strength to maintain its stability against them. It should have good drainage property and low constructionand maintenance cost. It is not mandatory to make the track aesthetic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "What does ‘M’ represent in the sleeper density formula M+7?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of rail in meters",
            "b) Length of sleepers in meters",
            "c) Length of sleepers in centimetres",
            "d) Length of rail in centimetres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sleeper density of a track can vary from M+7 to M+4 depending upon the weight and volume of traffic. Here M represents the length of rail in meters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Which method is mostly used for converting short welded rails to long welded rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flash butt welding",
            "b) Thermit welding",
            "c) Anderson welding",
            "d) Both Thermit and flash butt welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Thermit welding is used at site to convert short welded rails to long welded rails. Various fastenings such as screws, rail spikes and keys ae used to fix rails to sleepers. Flash butt welding is used to weld rails into three rail panels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "What does GMT stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gross million tensile strength",
            "b) Gross million tonnes per km/annum",
            "c) Giga metric tonnes",
            "d) Gauge metre tension per km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GMT stands for gross million tonnes per km/annum. It is used to denote the Traffic density of the route.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "What is the minimum ballast cushion provided for Concrete sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 500mm",
            "b) 250mm",
            "c) 125mm",
            "d) 1000mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A minimum depth of 250mm of ballast cushion must be provided for Concrete sleepers. This is according to the Metre gauge standard specification and enhances the stability of the track.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "What does an ‘S3’ route denote in case of MG track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uneconomical branch line",
            "b) Incomplete rail line",
            "c) Freight traffic route",
            "d) Hilly region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Speed and GMT are used to classify the tracks on MG routes. S1 route indicates through movement of freight traffic, S3 routes denote Uneconomic branch line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Why is the maintenance of Permanent way important?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To ensure safety of public",
            "b) For comfort of travellers",
            "c) To ensure safety and comfort of public",
            "d) To make the project economical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any glitch in the permanent way can lead to a major accident and harm the public. Thus its timely maintenance is important for protection and well-being of public.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Which among the following is an old method for track maintenance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Measured shovel packing",
            "b) Beater packing",
            "c) Mechanised maintenance",
            "d) Directed track maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Earlier manual maintenance of tracks by Beater packing was done. But after advancement in technology and increase in traffic modern methods are being used. These include measured shovel packing, mechanised maintenance and directed track maintenance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Over the years what has led to an increase in necessity for maintenance and improvement in track structures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased track loading",
            "b) Poor quality of tracks",
            "c) Poor formation strength",
            "d) Improper construction work"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In need based directed track maintenance system, work is done only when essentially required. This reduces excessive work and increases productivity of trackmen.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "What was the theory proposed by Zimmerman for the railway tracks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The track is an elastic structure",
            "b) The track is non elastic in nature",
            "c) Stresses are developed due to contact of rail and wheel",
            "d) The track is also subjected to lateral load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Zimmerman in 1888 proposed a theory which said that the track is an elastic structure. The sleepers provide elastic support to the rails. This elastic nature of rail helps in absorbing shocks and vibrations from the train.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "On what factors does the mode of distribution of load on the track depends upon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stiffness of the rails",
            "b) Weight of locomotive",
            "c) Stiffness of rail and elasticity of bed",
            "d) Stiffness of rail and weight of train"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The load acting on the track is distributed to the sleepers, ballast and the formation. Consequently Stiffness of rail and elasticity of bed are the factors which govern the mode of distribution of load.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The load in kilograms per unit rail length required to produce one unit depression in the rail is known as ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) section modulus",
            "b) track modulus",
            "c) stiffness coefficient of track",
            "d) tractive resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Track modulus defines the resistance to deformation in the track. It is a measure of the vertical rigidity of the rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "What is the unit of track modulus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) kg/cm2",
            "b) kg/cm",
            "c) Cubic tonnes",
            "d) kg2/m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Track modulus measures the resistance to deformation. It is defined as the load (kg) per unit rail length needed to cause unit deformation in rail. Its unit is kg/cm2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not responsible for the variation in track modulus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gauge",
            "b) Type of rail",
            "c) Cost of construction",
            "d) Ballast cushion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The track has voids in it. After initial loading these voids and slacks close. Thus after initial loading the depression per unit load decreases and becomes proportional to the increase in load.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "What are the types of track moduli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial track modulus",
            "b) Initial and Final track modulus",
            "c) Initial and Elastic track modulus",
            "d) Initial and Average track modulus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The track modulus depends upon the gauge and the Track standards. The properties of the railway track affect the deformation in the track and thus affect the track modulus.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of force acting on the track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vertical load",
            "b) Lateral force",
            "c) Magnetic force",
            "d) Contact stresses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The movement of locomotive on the track introduces various types of forces in it. These forces include Vertical loads, Lateral and longitudinal forces, Contact stresses, etc. There is absence of Magnetic field and thus no magnetic force.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Why is the value of dynamic load much more than that of static load?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Due to impact of speed and rail vibrations",
            "b) Additional live load during motion",
            "c) More traffic",
            "d) Both loads are same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the train is in motion additional load due to speed and vibrations in rail are experienced. Due to these factors accompanying the motion of the train, the dynamic load is more than the static load.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "What is the German formula for the speed factor of the train?",
        "Options": [
            "a) V/30,000",
            "b) V2/30,000",
            "c) V/3000",
            "d) V2/3000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dynamic load is more than the static load of the train. To find the dynamic load the static load is increased by a factor called the speed factor. The German formula for the speed factor of the train is V2/30,000.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Which is the major force developed due to revolving masses like pins and coupling rods in the wheel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centrifugal force",
            "b) Vertical force",
            "c) Lateral force",
            "d) Centripetal force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The crank pins and coupling rods make the centre of mass of the wheel to shift from its position. This creates an unbalanced force in the system which acts away from the centre of the wheel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "How is the lateral displacement of rail balanced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By coning of wheels",
            "b) By friction between rail and sleeper",
            "c) By manual means",
            "d) By electrical equipment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lateral deflection of the train causes huge development of bending moment in the wheels. This is balanced by the friction between rail and sleeper, ballast and rail and opposition presented by the fastenings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Hammer blow effect is because of the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) revolving masses like crank pins, coupling rods",
            "b) weight added to balance the reciprocating masses",
            "c) difference in elevation of inner and outer rail",
            "d) cant deficiency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The weight added to compensate the reciprocating masses tries to throw the wheel outwards. This causes pressure variation in the wheel and is known as Hammer blow effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "In the Hammer blow effect formula H = Mr(2πn)2 sinꬾ/g, what does n stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crank pin diameter",
            "b) Number of revolutions",
            "c) Number of revolutions per second",
            "d) Number of wheels in locomotive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the above equation, n stands for number of revolutions of the wheel per second. The diameter of the crank pin is ‘r’ and ‘ꬾ’ is the crank angle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "As per the theory of Hertz the rail and wheel contact is similar to the contact between _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) two cylinders",
            "b) a cylinder and a sphere",
            "c) a sphere and a cube",
            "d) two spheres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All these forces have different positions in wheel and thus have difference in phases. Thus they cannot obtain maximum value at the same time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The pattern of distribution of load under the sleepers does not depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Firmness of packing",
            "b) Cost of construction",
            "c) Sleepers",
            "d) Standard of maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The circular wheel is in contact with the curved surface of the wheel and their axes are at right angles to each other. According to the theory proposed by Hertz it depicts similar contact like two cylinders.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What is Photo-elastic method used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For measuring stresses on the rail",
            "b) For measuring strain of the rail",
            "c) For calculating depth of ballast",
            "d) For Reconnaissance survey"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The load pattern depends on the nature of load, the firmness of the packing under the sleeper and their maintenance. Distribution of load does not depend on the cost of construction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "What is the objective of coning of wheels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To save material",
            "b) For easy manufacturing of wheels",
            "c) For easy movement on curves",
            "d) For Aesthetic look"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rather than making the wheels flat they are sloped like a cone. This is done so that the wheels can traverse curves easily.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "What is the value of Slope provided to the wheels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 30",
            "b) 1 in 20",
            "c) 1 in 40",
            "d) 1 in 15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inner diameter of the wheels of the locomotive is greater than the outer diameter. The value of this slope is 1 in 20.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "What would be the result without coning of wheels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trains would have travelled slower",
            "b) The flange would have touched the rail",
            "c) Carrying capacity of the train would have reduced",
            "d) Passengers would feel more comfortable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Without coning of wheels the flat wheels might slip on the tracks during traversing a curve. This would lead to contact of flange and rail track. This would lead to uncomfortable journey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "What is the reason that disables the leading axle to take full advantage of the coning of wheels?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rigidity of the frame",
            "b) Unequal diameter of wheels",
            "c) Sharp curves",
            "d) More speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of the rigidity of the frame, while moving on a horizontal curve the rear axle moves inwards. Due to this the front axle is unable to take full advantage of coning of wheels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Which among the following is the correct formula for calculating the slip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slip=(2πθ/360)xG",
            "b) Slip=(πθ/360)xG",
            "c) Slip=(4πθ/360)xG",
            "d) Slip=(2πθ/360)xG2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the locomotive travels a curve centrifugal force acts on it. Due to this the outer wheel moves outwards and has to travel longer distance as compared to the inner wheel. Thus coning of wheels is done.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Why are the rails Tilted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To reduce wear and tear",
            "b) For cost efficiency",
            "c) For manufacturing ease",
            "d) To keep them in position"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum load of the wheel acts near the inner edge of the rail. This causes wear and tear of rails. For the reduction of wear and tear the rails are tilted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "What is the reason for development of Lateral Bending stresses in the rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tilting of rails",
            "b) Coning of wheels",
            "c) Centrifugal forces",
            "d) Eccentric loading of rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rails are tilted at a slope of 1 in 20 which is same as that of the wheel cone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which method is used for the Tilting of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adzing the wooden sleepers",
            "b) Providing canted bearing plates",
            "c) Strain method",
            "d) Adzing the wooden sleepers or by providing canted bearing plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The load of the wheel acts at a distance from the axis of the wheel. This creates eccentric loading which causes development of Lateral Bending stresses in the rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a function of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Serving as a lateral guide",
            "b) Providing a continuous surface",
            "c) To provide drainage",
            "d) To provide a level surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cant is provided to the railway track for proper drainage. Rails provide continuous, level surface and server as a lateral guide for wheels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Through which of the following Rails transmit the load acting on it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sleepers and Ballast",
            "b) Sleepers and fastenings",
            "c) Ballast",
            "d) Ballast and axle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wheels exert huge amount of forces on the rails. The rails transfer these forces to a larger formation below them. This is done through sleepers and ballast.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "The friction between the steel wheel and the steel rail is about ______ of the friction between the pneumatic tyre and a metalled road.",
        "Options": [
            "a) two fifth",
            "b) one fifth",
            "c) one tenth",
            "d) three fifth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The movement of trains is smooth because the rails offer very less resistance to it. The friction between wheel and rail is very less.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Why does Bull headed rails have more metal in the head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For aesthetic appearance",
            "b) To withstand wear and tear",
            "c) To make it rigid",
            "d) Because of manufacturing constrains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Every time a locomotive passes, huge amount of load is exerted on the rail. The rail remains in continuous contact with the chair. Because of this the bottom side of the rail is worn out and we cannot reuse it by inverting.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "What is a drawback of Bull headed rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chair is required for fixing",
            "b) They are very expensive",
            "c) They have short lives",
            "d) They are not good in appearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Huge amount of load on the rail causes damage to it. For better endurance and longer life the Bull headed rails have more metal in the head.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "What type of Cross section the flat-footed rail has?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Just like the Bull headed rails",
            "b) Inverted T type",
            "c) T type",
            "d) I type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bull headed rails can better withstand wear and tear and thus have long lives. But they require a chair so that they can be fixed with sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "What is used for the fixing of Flat footed rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chairs",
            "b) Spikes",
            "c) Nuts and bolts",
            "d) Chairs and other fastenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flat footed rail has inverted T type cross section. It is also called Vignole rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "Which rail has been standardised for adoption on the Indian railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bull headed",
            "b) Double headed",
            "c) Flat footed",
            "d) Combination of BH and DH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flat footed rails do not need any chair type arrangement for fixing on sleepers. Spikes are used for this purpose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Where should the centre of gravity of the rail section be located?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Near to the bottom of the rail",
            "b) close to the upper portion",
            "c) close to the mid height",
            "d) Can be anywhere between the section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Huge number of stresses act on the railway track. For balancing the tensile and compressive stresses the centre of gravity of the rail section should be located near the mid height of the rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of the rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Head",
            "b) Web",
            "c) Ballast",
            "d) Foot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rail consists of three parts, a head, a web and a foot. Ballast is a separate component which is not a part of the rail section.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "What is the reason that the head should have sufficient depth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To sustain vertical wear",
            "b) For lateral stiffness",
            "c) To make it cheap",
            "d) For proper maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For enduring vertical wear the head should have sufficient depth. For desired lateral stiffness it is made wider.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Why is the foot made wide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To avoid corrosion",
            "b) To avoid overturning",
            "c) For making it cost efficient",
            "d) For easy manufacturing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The foot should be made wide enough to provide stability to the rail. It should resist the forces applied and should not be overturned.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "The Factors like heaviest axle load, max permissible speed, depth of Ballast cushion are considered for deciding the _____ of the rail.",
        "Options": [
            "a) weight",
            "b) length",
            "c) section",
            "d) weight and section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A rail is designated by its weight per unit length. Its weight and section are decided after considering factors like heaviest axle load, speed, Ballast cushion etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "What will be the maximum axle load (in tonnes) for rails of 52kg/m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 29.12t",
            "b) 30t",
            "c) 37.62t",
            "d) 22.5t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum axle load=560 x sectional weight of rail\n                                                           =560 x 52kg/m\n                                                           =29120kg\n                                                           =29.12tonnes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Long rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It’s difficult to manufacture long rails",
            "b) More internal stresses in long rails",
            "c) Easy transportation facilities for long rails",
            "d) Longer rails are economical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Longer rails are much more economical and comfortable for rides. This is because longer rails reduce the number of joints, fittings and overall maintenance cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "What is duplex process used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manufacturing of steel for rails",
            "b) Manufacturing of bolts",
            "c) Coning of wheels",
            "d) Transportation of wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Duplex or open hearth processes can be used for the manufacturing of steel which is used for making rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "What is done to distinguish the rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are colour coded",
            "b) They have numbers",
            "c) They are manufactured by different processes",
            "d) They cannot be distinguished"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rails need to be distinguished based on grade, class, length, etc. For this all the rails are colour coded.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "What is the value of Tolerance for Horizontal straightness of Class A rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3mm",
            "b) 1mm",
            "c) 0.5mm",
            "d) 0.8mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rails should be unconditionally straight. A deviation of 0.5mm for class A rails is acceptable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "What is the Tup test also known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hammer blow test",
            "b) Falling weight test",
            "c) Deviation test",
            "d) Compressibility test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Falling weight test is done for checking the serviceability of the rails. The rail should not be deformed after the tup of specified weight falls on it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "What is the height from which the weight is dropped in falling weight test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10m",
            "b) 7.2m",
            "c) 9.8m",
            "d) 6m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A specified weight is dropped from a height of 7.2m on the rail. For every cast of 100metric tonnes one falling weight test is done.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The tensile strength of the rail should not be less than ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100kg/mm",
            "b) 85kg/m2",
            "c) 72kg/mm2",
            "d) 98kg/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rail must possess a minimum tensile strength of 72kg/mm2. Along with this it should have a minimum elongation of 14% for medium manganese rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "Where are third quality rails used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Industrial sidings",
            "b) Steep gradients",
            "c) Hilly regions",
            "d) They cannot be used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rails which do not obey to the standards of first and second quality rails are called as third quality rails. They can be used in industrial sidings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Third quality rails are painted by which colour on the end face?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Black",
            "b) White",
            "c) Yellow",
            "d) Red"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: At end of the rails, flanges are painted white for a length of 500mm from each end. This is done for easy identification of the rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "What is the advantage of End hardened rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy to manufacture",
            "b) Less End batter",
            "c) Maximum end batter",
            "d) Less cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 90 UTS rails have hardness of about 270 BHN which is much more than that of 220BHN of Manganese rails with 72UTS. Thus they are more resilient to wear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "What is done for hardening of Head hardened rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passed through a thermal treatment plant",
            "b) Application of oil",
            "c) Hammer test",
            "d) Different material used"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rails which are hardened at ends by using oil or water quenching are called end hardened rails. They have less end batter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Where does maximum lateral wear of rail occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) On curves",
            "b) On flat gradient",
            "c) On steep gradient",
            "d) Same everywhere"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Centrifugal forces act on the locomotive while traversing curves. This causes lateral thrust development which leads to more lateral wear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for wear and tear of rails in coastal areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Humidity",
            "b) Weather effects",
            "c) Humidity and weather effects",
            "d) Extra force applied by the engine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rails may face additional wear and tear in coastal areas and tunnels due to humidity and weather changes. Extra force is applied by engine on steep gradients.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The difference in height of the rail at end and at a point 30cm away from the end is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rail end batter",
            "b) Slope of rail",
            "c) Coning of wheel",
            "d) Gradient of rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to moving loads the end of the rails wears in some time. Thus a height difference is created and is called rail end batter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Where are rail lubricators used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) On sharp curves",
            "b) On steep rails",
            "c) On narrow gauges",
            "d) On cast iron sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lateral wear at sharp curves is very high. Rail lubricators are used to lubricate the gauge face on the outer rail on sharp curves to reduce friction which subsequently reduces wear and tear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods cannot be used for measurement of wear of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By weighing the rail",
            "b) By using instruments",
            "c) Chain and tape",
            "d) Profiling with the help of needles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wear of rail cannot be measured by chain and tape because it’s minute. Methods like profiling of section or weighing of rails is used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Interchanging inner and outer rails will lead to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimising wear of rails",
            "b) Increasing wear of rails",
            "c) Change in cant",
            "d) Increasing rail end batter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Outer rails are more damaged as compared to inner rails on curves. Interchanging them can reduce wear and increase their service life.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "What can be done to prevent Hogging of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tilting of rails",
            "b) Shovel packing",
            "c) Scabbing of rails",
            "d) Interchanging rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hogging of rail can happen because of poor maintenance, faulty fastenings, etc. It can be prevented by measured shovel packing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "In which type of defect patches of metal fall from the rail table?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scabbing of rails",
            "b) Hogging of rails",
            "c) Wheel burns",
            "d) Corrugation of rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A metal chunk generally falls from the rail in case of scabbing of rails. An elliptical depression is created with cracks surrounding it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "What causes wheel burns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slipping of wheel on rail surface",
            "b) Falling of metal chunks",
            "c) Manufacturing defects",
            "d) High speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Slipping of wheel of locomotive on rail causes generation of extra heat. This affects the rail surface and a depression on the rail surface is created leading to wheel burns.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following locations are less likely to develop wheel burns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steep gradients",
            "b) Heavy braking incidences",
            "c) Near water columns",
            "d) On flat gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Wheel burns are generally found on steep gradients because there is less chance of slipping of wheels on flat gradients. Sometimes, more heat is generated in braking operations and leads to wheel burns.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Which of the following defects occur because of heavy bearing pressure on small area of contact?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shelling and Black spots",
            "b) Scabbing of wheels",
            "c) Hogging of wheels",
            "d) Corrugation of wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Huge internal stresses are produced because of heavy pressure on small area. This causes horizontal separation of metal. This defect is called as Shelling and black spots.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "What can be done for removing Corrugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grinding the rail head",
            "b) Shovel packing",
            "c) Tilting of rails",
            "d) Scabbing of rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Locking of air takes place when vehicles pass over corrugated rails. This produces a sound similar to roaring and is called Roaring of rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "What is a reason of premature failure of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inherent defects in metal",
            "b) Tilting of rails",
            "c) Change in gauge width",
            "d) Loose ballast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sometimes rails are not able to carry the minimum GMT they are designed for. This can be because of the inherent defect in metal and leads to premature failure of rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of inherent defect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Faulty chemical composition",
            "b) Harmful segregation",
            "c) Wearing of rails",
            "d) Seams and laps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wearing of rails is caused because of continuous effect of huge loads. The other defects are inherent defects in rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following leads to excessive corrosion of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Presence of chlorides",
            "b) Exposure to moisture and humidity",
            "c) Improper maintenance of tracks",
            "d) Presence of chlorides and exposure to moisture and humidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corrosion of rails is due to weather conditions like excess humidity and moisture content. Presence of salts like chlorides also contribute to corrosion of rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "What does the first part of the code used for classification of rail failure consist of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three code letters",
            "b) Three code digits",
            "c) Combination of letters and digits",
            "d) Colour codes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Identification of failed rails can be easy if they are coded. The code consists of two parts, three code letters and three or four code digits.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Which letter is used for points and crossing rails in the code used for classification of rail failures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X",
            "b) O",
            "c) Y",
            "d) P"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Points and crossings are denoted by letter X. O is used for plain rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "What is the reason for withdrawal of rail if letter ‘C’ is used in code?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excessive corrosion",
            "b) Cracked rail",
            "c) Fracture",
            "d) Derailment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Letter ‘C’ is used if the reason for withdrawal of rail is cracking of rail. Excessive corrosion is the cause of failure of rail. F and D are used for fracture and derailment respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "What does the third letter represent in the First portion of the code used for classification of rail failures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Probable cause of failure",
            "b) Type of rail used",
            "c) Reason for withdrawal of rail",
            "d) Location of fracture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first portion of the code consist of three letters. Out of this the third one is used for representing the probable cause of failure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "What does the first digit of the second portion of the code represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cause of failure",
            "b) Location of fracture on length of the rail",
            "c) Direction of crack",
            "d) Direction of fracture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first digit of the second portion of the code gives the location of fracture on length of the rail. ‘1’ is used for within fish plate limits and ‘2’ for other portions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which digit is used to tell that the failure in the rail section has started from within the rail head?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Any number between 0-9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The digit ‘1’ is used for within the rail head, ‘2’ for surface of rail head and ‘3’ for web. Zero is used if the position of rail section is unknown and ‘4’ is used for foot.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "How can rail flaws be detected?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By visual examination",
            "b) By rail flaw detection equipment",
            "c) By visual examination or equipment",
            "d) By using chemicals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flaws are the defects which can lead to fracture of rails. Thus their detection is important and can be done visually or with the help of equipment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "What is another name of Ultrasonic rail flaw detection technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-destructive method of testing",
            "b) Destructive method of testing",
            "c) Method of visual examination",
            "d) Metallurgical flaw detection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rails/joints are not opened in USFD method. This method is also called Non-destructive method of testing of rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "What is the minimum frequency of ultrasonic waves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20,000 cycles per second",
            "b) 25,000 cycles per second",
            "c) 31,400 cycles per second",
            "d) 25,000 cycles per minute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ultrasonic waves are the waves having frequency more than 20,000 cycles per second. They follow principles of reflection, refraction and transmission.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "How defects are identified using ultrasonic waves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They pass through the flaw",
            "b) They reflect back from the flaw",
            "c) They give sound when encountered a flaw",
            "d) They release heat at location of flaw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the ultrasonic waves detect a flaw they have a property of reflecting back. This is used for detection of defects in the rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Crystal transducers are used for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Production of ultrasonic frequency",
            "b) Measuring the cracks in rails",
            "c) Shaping the wheels",
            "d) Production of sound"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crystal transducers are made of Barium or Quartz and are the simplest method used for production of ultrasonic frequency. This is then used for detection of flaws.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Which probe is suitable for detecting horizontal and inclined flaws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Normal probe",
            "b) Angle probe",
            "c) Semi normal probe",
            "d) Crystal probe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Normal probes transmit the ultrasonic waves in downward direction. They can be used to detect horizontal, inclined flaws and bolt hole cracks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques is used by Indian railways for ultrasonic testing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmission",
            "b) Resonance",
            "c) Frequency modulation",
            "d) Acoustic range"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Different techniques are adopted depending on the type of equipment involved. Indian railway uses pulse echo as well as frequency modulation methods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "How is the echo arising due to fault determined using pulse echo system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By its relative position",
            "b) By its amplitude",
            "c) By its range",
            "d) By its relative position and amplitude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When ultrasonic waves are sent they may have more than one reflection. But the one corresponding to a fault is easily recognized by its relative position and amplitude.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "What does IMR stand for in the classification of Rail flaws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immediate removal",
            "b) Intentional removal",
            "c) Intermediate repetition",
            "d) Incremental repetition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: IMR stands for immediate removal. These flaws are serious in nature and can lead to accidents. Rails having such flaws should be replaced quickly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "What type of defect is OBS defect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Not so serious",
            "b) Immediate removal",
            "c) Warning of early removal",
            "d) Safe rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: OBS stands for observe. These defects are not so serious and rail has to be kept under observation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "An OBS(E) designation represents a defect ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) On major bridges",
            "b) Within the fish plate",
            "c) Anywhere on the track",
            "d) At joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A defect around 100m from approach of a bridge is designated as OBS(B). OBS(E) stands for defect within fish plate zone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used for testing of long railway tracks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) German rail testing car",
            "b) Manual methods",
            "c) Rail testing trolley",
            "d) Mechanical gauges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rail testing trolley can test only 2-3 km of rail in a day. Thus German rail testing car can be used which tests around 200km per day efficiently.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "What is the frequency prescribed for the need based concept of the ultrasonic testing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 GMT",
            "b) 8 GMT",
            "c) 10 GMT",
            "d) 6 GMT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inspection of rails can be done after the passage of every 8GMT of load. Thus, frequency for need based ultrasonic testing is 8GMT.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "What does SPURT stand for in SPURT car procured by the Indian railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Self-propelled Ultrasonic Rail Testing",
            "b) Self-programmed Ultrasonic Rail Testing",
            "c) Satellite Proposed Universal Rail Testing",
            "d) Series Processed Unit for Rail Testing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cracks completely below the bolt holes remain undetected by the frequency modulation technique. This is because of the interruptions caused by the hole.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is false?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sleepers hold the rail in correct gauge",
            "b) Sleepers transfer load from ballast to rails",
            "c) Sleepers offer support to the rails",
            "d) Sleepers hold rails in correct alignment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sleepers hold the rail in correct gauge and alignment, offer support to them but do not transfer the load from the ballast to the rails. They transfer the load coming on the rails from the wheels to the ballast.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Why is it necessary for the sleepers to act as an elastic structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To absorb the vibrations of moving loads",
            "b) To make it cheap",
            "c) It is the material’s limitation",
            "d) To keep them intact"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Huge amount of loads and vibrations act on the rails because of the moving load. By making the sleepers elastic we ensure proper transfer and absorption of these.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a requirement of the design of the sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It should be fixed and removed easily",
            "b) Track circuiting should be possible",
            "c) Maintenance cost should be minimum",
            "d) Bearing area should be sufficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sleepers should be designed to have sufficient bearing area, easy handling and easy track circuiting. The maintenance cost is not a design criteria, but it is an important requirement of the sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The number of sleepers per rail length is called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) sleeper spacing",
            "b) sleeper density",
            "c) sleeper gravity",
            "d) sleeper gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of sleepers laid on the track per rail length is termed as sleeper density. Based on the sleeper density the spacing between sleepers is calculated. The maximum traffic on a route has an impact on its sleeper density.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "What does ‘M’ represent in the sleeper density formula M + x?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of rail in metres",
            "b) Axle load",
            "c) Length of sleepers",
            "d) Type of route"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sleeper density is represented by the formula M + x. Here ‘M’ is the length of rail and ‘x’ depends on various factors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "In the sleeper density formula M + x, x does not vary according to which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type and section of rails",
            "b) Type of ballast",
            "c) The axle load of train",
            "d) The slope of track"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: X varies according to factors like axle load and speed, ballast cushion, strength of sleepers and type of rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Why the sleepers are closely spaced near the joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because of weakness of joints",
            "b) Because of coning of wheels",
            "c) Because of tilting of rails",
            "d) Because of more load at joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The joints are the weakest portion of the rail. Thus sleepers are more closely placed around them so that they do not fail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Other than sleeper density how can the number of sleepers can be represented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of sleepers per kilometre",
            "b) Depending of the slope",
            "c) Depending on the formation width",
            "d) Width of sleepers per kilometre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of sleepers on track can be specified by number of sleepers per kilometre of track. Example: 1400 sleepers/km.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of sleepers have the maximum service life?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wooden",
            "b) Steel",
            "c) Cast Iron",
            "d) Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Concrete sleepers have the best service life and are being extensively used in Indian railways nowadays. Whereas wooden sleepers have the least service life.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of Concrete sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High weight",
            "b) High maintenance cost",
            "c) Mechanised maintenance only",
            "d) Good service life"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Concrete sleepers are bulky but have low maintenance cost. They always need a mechanised system for maintenance and cannot be maintained manually.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Which of the following sleepers cannot be damaged by white ants but corrosion can occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cast Iron",
            "b) Wooden",
            "c) Steel",
            "d) Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wooden sleepers can be damaged by ants, CI by corrosion and concrete by neither. Steel sleepers cannot be damaged by ants but can be corroded.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Which sleepers require insulating pads for track circuiting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wooden sleepers",
            "b) Steel and CI sleepers",
            "c) Concrete sleepers",
            "d) Steel sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Track circuiting is easy for concrete sleepers and is finest in case of wooden sleepers. But it is difficult in Steel and CI sleepers which makes the provision of insulating pads necessary.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Which type of sleeper has the maximum creep?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wooden",
            "b) Concrete",
            "c) Steel",
            "d) Cast Iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Creep can be defined as the forward movement of rails with respect to sleepers. Wooden sleepers have the maximum creep and it is least in case of concrete sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "The scrap value of concrete is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) None",
            "b) High",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Higher than wooden"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Concrete sleepers once used do not give any scrap value. Concrete once set hard cannot be remoulded into another shape. Thus these sleepers cannot be reused for any productive work.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "What is the importance of the depth of a sleeper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It directs its stiffness",
            "b) It controls the bearing area",
            "c) It makes the rails stronger",
            "d) It lessens the maintenance cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sleeper should have adequate stiffness as they receive load from wheels. They act as a beam and should have proper depth which administers its stiffness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "What is governed by the length and width of the sleeper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The bearing area",
            "b) Cant value",
            "c) Drainage properties",
            "d) Stiffness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bearing area is the area which bears all the load acting on the sleeper. It is governed by the length and width of the sleeper.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "The index used to determine the suitability of a particular timber for use as a sleeper is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Composite strength index",
            "b) Composite sleeper index",
            "c) Compressive strength index",
            "d) Compressive sleeper index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CSI i.e. the Composite sleeper index determines the suitability of a timber to be used as a sleeper with reference to its mechanical strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "What is the formula for the Composite sleeper index of a wooden sleeper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CSI = (S + 10H)/20",
            "b) CSI = (S + 10H)/10",
            "c) CSI = (S + 20H)/20",
            "d) CSI = (S + 5H)/20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Composite sleeper index has advanced from a combination of properties of strength and hardness of the sleeper. The correct formula for Composite sleeper index of a wooden sleeper is given by CSI = (S + 10H)/20.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "What does ‘S’ stand for in the CSI equation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) General strength for green timber at 12% moisture content",
            "b) General strength for dry timber at 12% moisture content",
            "c) General strength for both green and dry timber at 12% moisture content",
            "d) General strength for both green and dry timber at 15% moisture content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the CSI equation ‘S’ is the general strength for both green and dry timber at 12% moisture content. ‘H’ is the general hardness for green and dry timber at 12% moisture content.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of the wooden sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are cheap",
            "b) They have less scrap value",
            "c) They can be used even without stone Ballast",
            "d) They can be easily handled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wooden sleepers have advantages like less cost, easy handling and they can be used even without stone ballast. But their scrap value is almost negligible which is a disadvantage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a major reason for less service life of wooden sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attack by ants",
            "b) Wear because of load",
            "c) Decay due to various conditions",
            "d) Less scrap value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Service life of wooden sleepers can be decreased due to factors like attack by ants, wear because of heavy load and decaying of material. Though wooden sleepers have negligible scrap value but it is not a reason for less service life.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Centre heart, knots, split ends are basically the types of ______ found in wooden sleepers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Defects",
            "b) Fastenings",
            "c) Joints",
            "d) strength properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The wooden sleepers obtained from the State forest departments have major defects in them. These may include Centre heart, knots, split ends, cross grains, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "According to the recommendations of the committee of the railway board what should be used compulsorily when traffic density exceeds 20GMT on BG routes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bearing plates",
            "b) Colour codes",
            "c) Stone ballast",
            "d) Concrete sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The committee said bearing plates must be used when traffic density exceeds 20GMT on BG routes and 5GMT on MG routes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which type of sleepers do not require any treatment and can be directly laid on the track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-durable type",
            "b) Durable type",
            "c) Treated type",
            "d) Untreated type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Durable sleepers are the ones which do not require any treatment before laying on track. These are sleepers produced from timbers like teak, Sal, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "What will happen if Non-durable type of sleepers are used without any treatment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decay of sleeper will take place",
            "b) The sleeper will not fit properly",
            "c) Fastenings will not work",
            "d) It won’t cause any harm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Non-durable sleepers have short life spans if they are laid without treatment. Also it will cause quick decay of sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "What is timber produced from trees with broad leaves also known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soft wood",
            "b) Durable wood",
            "c) Hard wood",
            "d) Treated wood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wooden sleepers can be called hard and soft wood based on origin. Timber obtained from trees with broad leaves is known as hard wood.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "The sleepers made of wood from naturally durable species are classified as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) treated sleepers",
            "b) durable sleepers",
            "c) untreated sleepers",
            "d) non-durable sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wooden sleepers are classified into two categories, Treated and Untreated sleepers. Untreated sleepers consist of sleepers made from naturally durable species. The rest of the sleepers are called Treated sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "What is another name of Full cell method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bethell process",
            "b) Rueping process",
            "c) Lowry process",
            "d) Andrew process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are three methods for forcing of preservative into the wood for treatment of sleepers. Among them, Rueping and Lowry process are names of empty cell methods. Bethell process is full cell process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "In which process maximum retention of hot creosote oil is practiced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Full cell process",
            "b) Empty cell process",
            "c) Seasoning of sleepers",
            "d) Prophylactic treatment of sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Full cell (Bethell) process uses creosote oil. This process is used when maximum withholding of creosote oil is required.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Why a final vacuum is applied in the Full cell process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To free the timber of excessive preservative",
            "b) To add extra preservative",
            "c) To maintain equilibrium",
            "d) To drain the creosote oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Excessive preservative may cause damage to the sleeper. Thus a vacuum of 55cm of mercury is applied to remove excess preservative.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "Empty cell (Rueping) process is used for treating which type of timber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hard timber",
            "b) Porous timber",
            "c) Soft wood",
            "d) Deodar timber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sleepers made from Deodar are treated using full cell process. Empty cell (Rueping) process is used for treating Porous timber.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Where are Fir sleepers used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lines with traffic density less than 10GMT",
            "b) Lines with traffic density less than 30GMT",
            "c) All main lines",
            "d) All trunk routes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fir sleepers are used only when the main or trunk lines have traffic density less than 10GMT. They do not provide good service.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "What is the order for recovery of preservatives in these processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rueping process < Lowry process < Bethell process",
            "b) Rueping process > Lowry process > Bethell process",
            "c) Rueping process < Lowry process < Bethell process",
            "d) Rueping process = Lowry process = Bethell process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Rueping process air is entrapped inside the cell, thus it limits the absorption of preservative. Therefore, recovery of preservative is maximum in Rueping process and least in Full cell process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Why is prophylactic treatment of sleepers done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To prevent infection at the treatment plant",
            "b) To make it stronger",
            "c) To remove excess preservative",
            "d) To remove creosote oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Considerable time is required for transferring sleepers from forest to plant. Thus prophylactic treatment is given for prevention of infection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "What is used for removing the moisture content in Boulton process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water (cold)",
            "b) Hot preservative",
            "c) Natural air",
            "d) Prophylactic treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Boulton or boiling under vacuum process uses hot preservative for removing moisture content from unseasoned wood.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way of stacking of sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One and nine method",
            "b) Close crib method",
            "c) Open crib method",
            "d) Nine and one method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Moisture content in case of sleepers to be treated by pressure treatment should not be more than 25%. Seasoning of sleepers is done to reduce this moisture content. Lowering of moisture content helps in effective treatment of the sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "In which type of sleepers the heartwood side is kept upwards and the sapwood side downwards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Treated sleepers",
            "b) Untreated sleepers",
            "c) Both treated and untreated sleepers",
            "d) Neither treated nor untreated sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For air seasoning of sleepers they are stacked in various ways. This includes one and nine method, Close crib method and Open crib method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "This process of cutting the wooden sleeper at a slope of 1 in 20 is known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) adzing of wooden sleepers",
            "b) laying of wooden sleepers",
            "c) seasoning of sleepers",
            "d) prophylactic treatment of sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In untreated sleepers sapwood side is kept downwards. This is done because sapwood side contains more creosote and is liable to less damage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Which is the most used method for seasoning of wooden sleepers in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air seasoning",
            "b) Artificial seasoning",
            "c) Boulton seasoning",
            "d) Kiln seasoning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sleepers are to be tilted inward at a cant of I in 20. For this cutting of sleepers has to be done which is called as adzing of wooden sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Why were steel channel sleepers developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because of shortage of wooden sleepers",
            "b) They are cheap",
            "c) They are easily manufactured",
            "d) They do not require fastenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Wooden sleepers are obtained from cutting of trees. Shortage of trees led to the development of steel channel sleepers. They are predominantly used on girder bridges.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "The sleepers made from waste products are called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Composite sleepers",
            "b) Durable sleepers",
            "c) Workable sleepers",
            "d) Treated sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Composite sleepers developed to replace wooden sleepers were made from waste materials such as used rubber tyres. They have a claimed life span of around 40years.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Which type of fittings are used by Composite sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Similar to that of wooden sleepers",
            "b) Twice the strength of wooden sleepers",
            "c) Rubber fastenings",
            "d) They do not require fittings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fastenings are required to hold the rail and the sleeper together. Composite sleepers show similarities with wooden sleepers. Thus they also have similar fittings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Where are composite sleepers developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In USA",
            "b) In India",
            "c) In Japan",
            "d) In Russia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Composite sleepers have been developed indigenously by Indian railways in India. They can be used on tracks if they give appreciable results after testing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about steel trough sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long life",
            "b) Liable to decay",
            "c) Good lateral rigidity",
            "d) Simple manufacturing process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Steel trough sleepers are not liable to decay like wooden sleepers. They do not decay and aren’t attacked by vermin.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "What type of problems are observed in case of pressed up lugs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maintenance problems",
            "b) Cost inefficiency",
            "c) Improper fitting",
            "d) They are easily decayed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to vibrations the pressed up lugs cause movement of keys. Thus they require frequent and efficient maintenance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "What is the limit for inward tilt at rail seat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 15 to 1 in 25",
            "b) 1 in 20 to 1 in 25",
            "c) 1 in 15 to 1 in 20",
            "d) 1 in 10 to 1 in 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steel trough sleepers provide good lateral stability and can be used easily along with fastenings. Consequently they can be used with long welded rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "What mark is given to first quality sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A yellow cross",
            "b) A green dot",
            "c) A red strip",
            "d) A green strip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The limit for inward tilt at rail seat is from 1 in 15 to 1 in 25. The sleepers are termed defective otherwise.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Which sleepers are marked with a cross in yellow paint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Second quality sleepers",
            "b) Sleepers unfit for use",
            "c) Sleepers rejected as first quality but free from defects",
            "d) Third quality sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A green dot indicates that the sleepers are of first quality. A 15cm wide strip of yellow paint is used to mark all second quality steel trough sleepers. This is done to avoid mixing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true about cast iron sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are difficult to manufacture",
            "b) Less scrap value",
            "c) Difficult gauge maintenance",
            "d) Good lateral stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cast iron sleepers have bars which get bent over time. This makes gauge maintenance difficult.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "What is the full form of CST-9 sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Central Standard Trial-9",
            "b) Central Strength Tally-9",
            "c) Compressive Strength Target-9",
            "d) Cast Steel Trial-9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The inspection and maintenance of Cast iron pot sleepers is inconvenient and difficult. This is because the fittings are hidden.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Why were CST-9 sleepers available with reverse jaws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) For anti-sabotage measures",
            "b) For making it attractive",
            "c) For easy manufacturing",
            "d) Less wear and tear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CST stands for Central Standard Trial. 9 represents that the sleeper is ninth in the series made by the Central Standard Office.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about the CST-9 sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Not suitable for mechanical maintenance with tie hammers",
            "b) Limited strength to hold LWRs",
            "c) Very less lateral stability",
            "d) Needs more attention"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Usually three reverse jaw CST-9 sleepers are provided per rail. This is done to prevent any damage or theft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "What is used to hold the rail in case of CST-10 sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed lug and key",
            "b) Double coil spring washers",
            "c) Clips and keys",
            "d) Elastic fastenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The CST-9 sleepers provide considerably good stability. But requires constant attention.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "What is used in CST-11 sleepers to accommodate the pandrol clip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double coil spring washers",
            "b) A shoulder is provided",
            "c) Lugs and keys",
            "d) Single coil washer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CST-9 sleepers use fixed lug and key. CST-10 sleepers use Double coil spring washers for holding the rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Which of the following sleepers is used by the Indian railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CST-9",
            "b) CST-13",
            "c) CST-11",
            "d) CST-12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The CST-11 has an improvement over CST-10 sleeper that a shoulder is provided for Pandrol clip. Double coil spring washers are not used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Concrete sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They have long lifespans",
            "b) They can be mass produced",
            "c) They have high scrap value",
            "d) They are not liable to corrosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Concrete sleepers have long service life and do not corrode. But they have no scrap value because concrete once set hard cannot be remoulded or reused.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Why concrete sleepers can be used in Track circuited areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are heavy",
            "b) They are bad conductors of electricity",
            "c) They do not corrode",
            "d) They are easy to handle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Concrete sleepers are inflammable and do not corrode. They are bad conductors of electricity and thus can be used in track circuited areas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "The monoblock prestressed concrete sleepers are similar to which sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) German B-58",
            "b) PCS-12 and PCS-14",
            "c) Cast Iron sleepers",
            "d) Mono block post-tension concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mono-block prestressed concrete sleepers have a length of 2750mm and 270kg weight. They are similar to German B-58 type of sleeper.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "What is the general 28-day crushing strength of concrete for mono block prestressed concrete type sleeper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 525kg/cm2",
            "b) 600kg/cm2",
            "c) 1676kg/cm2",
            "d) 100kg/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 28-day crushing strength of concrete for this sleeper should not be less than 525kg/cm2. The initial prestressing of steel is 100kg/cm2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Why is the manufacturing cost of mono-block prestressed concrete sleepers more?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They have ties",
            "b) They require prestressed concrete",
            "c) They have long life",
            "d) They break easily"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In two-block concrete sleepers the tie has shorter life span. Thus mono block sleepers have longer life than two-block concrete sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What guides the train from one line of rail tracks to another?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turnout",
            "b) Ballast",
            "c) Gauge",
            "d) Fastenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Two-block concrete sleepers require simple RCC for manufacturing. Thus they are cheap than mono-block prestressed concrete sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "In post tensioned type of sleeper how is the force transferred to the concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Through positive anchors",
            "b) Through bonds",
            "c) Through bonds and positive anchors",
            "d) Through fastenings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Turnout is a mechanism which enables the trains to move from one track to another. Fastenings are used to hold various components of the track together.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which method is used for manufacturing of mono-block concrete sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short-line method",
            "b) Long-line method",
            "c) Lorry method",
            "d) Ultimate stress method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In post tensioned type of sleeper the force transferred to the concrete is only through positive anchors. But in pre-tensioned it is through bonds and positive anchors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a function of Ballast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing a bed for sleepers",
            "b) Holding sleepers in position",
            "c) Providing effective drainage",
            "d) Providing resistance to wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ballast provides resistance to the track and not wheels for proper stability. It should provide effective drainage, proper bed for sleepers and hols the sleepers in position.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Which element transfers its load directly to the Ballast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sleepers",
            "b) Wheels",
            "c) Locomotive",
            "d) Formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The sleepers transfer the load imposed on it directly to the ballast. The Ballast which in turn transfers it to the formation and thus works efficiently.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Previously which of the following ballast was used for flat bottom sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50mm",
            "b) 36mm",
            "c) 25mm",
            "d) 74mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ballast provides elasticity to the track. This maintains comfortable conditions for the passengers during movement of the train especially while moving on curves.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following ballast is used at points and crossings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50mm",
            "b) 40mm",
            "c) 25mm",
            "d) 72mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Earlier 50mm (2”) ballast was used for concrete and wooden sleepers. 40mm (1.5”) ballast was used for metal sleepers. Now to ensure uniformity 50mm ballast are used on all types of sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Where can sand ballast be used with wooden and steel trough sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only coarse sand can be used",
            "b) Areas with low traffic density",
            "c) Areas with steep slope",
            "d) Areas with less rainfall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sand ballast is usually used for cast iron pots. It can be used with steel and wooden sleepers where traffic density is low.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of sand ballast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Provides good drainage",
            "b) Can be blown off easily",
            "c) Causes excessive wear",
            "d) Cannot be blown off easily"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sand being light in weight has a drawback of blowing off. It provides good drainage but also causes excessive wear of the track which is undesirable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "The decomposition of laterite results in the formation of _______ ballast.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moorum",
            "b) Coal ash",
            "c) Broken stone",
            "d) Sand ballast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Moorum is red or yellow in colour and formed by the decomposition of laterite. Broken stone block is generally acquired from hard stones like granite and quartzite.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Why the moorum can be used as a blanketing material for black cotton soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its red in colour",
            "b) It is formed by laterite",
            "c) It prevents percolation of water",
            "d) It is easy to handle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Moorum prevents percolation of water in formation. This percolated water can lead to softening of formation. Moorum can also be used as initial ballast or sub ballast.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most used ballast on Indian railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand ballast",
            "b) Broken stone ballast",
            "c) Brickbat ballast",
            "d) Coal ash ballast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coal ash ballast is cheap but it has corrosive action. This can lead to damage of steel sleepers and fittings and their frequent maintenance will be required.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Which of the following ballast is usually used in yards and sidings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coal ash",
            "b) Broken stone",
            "c) Moorum",
            "d) Sand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Broken stone ballast is the most used ballast on Indian railways. It is economical in the long run and can be used for high speed tracks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "The pressure distribution in the ballast section does not depend on which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape of ballast",
            "b) Size of ballast",
            "c) Cant of track",
            "d) Degree of consolidation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Load is transferred from sleeper to formation through ballast. The pressure distribution depends upon the degree of consolidation, size and shape of ballast.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for calculating the depth of ballast cushion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sleeper spacing = width of the sleeper + 3 × depth of ballast",
            "b) Sleeper spacing = width of the sleeper + depth of ballast",
            "c) Sleeper spacing = width of the sleeper + 2 × depth of ballast",
            "d) Sleeper spacing = 3 x width of the sleeper + 2 × depth of ballast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The depth of the ballast cushion can be calculated by using the sleeper spacing and width of sleeper. Sleeper spacing = width of the sleeper + 2 × depth of ballast.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the pressure lines formed due to the dispersion of load in the ballast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bulb shaped",
            "b) Straight lines",
            "c) Parabola",
            "d) Triangular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lines of same pressure are bulb shaped. But for convenience we take the load dispersion at an angle of 45° to the vertical.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a requirement of a good ballast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tough",
            "b) Wear resistant",
            "c) Rounded",
            "d) Cheap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dwarf walls of suitable properties are provided in case of cuttings. This is to protect or retain the ballast in case when speed of the locomotive is very high.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Why should the ballast be hard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) So that it does not get crushed",
            "b) So that it can absorb water",
            "c) To allow good drainage",
            "d) To keep it cheap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ballast should not be rounded. It should generally be cubical having sharp edges. This is regarding the shear strength provided by the Ballast.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "What should be the maximum percentage of aggregates retained on the 65mm sieve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 5%",
            "c) 16%",
            "d) 12%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The aggregates used for Ballast should be present in proper proportion with respect to their sizes. Not more than 5% should be retained on 65mm sieve and 40-60% on 40 mm sieve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "What should be the shape of Ballast stones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cubical",
            "b) Rounded",
            "c) Sub-rounded",
            "d) Flaky"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ballast must be cubical in shape and the particles should not be flaky. Minimum rounded faces should be present. Shape affects the resistance to abrasion, packing efficiency and strength of the ballast.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "What is the shrinkage allowance when ballast is supplied by Wagons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 8%",
            "d) 32%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ballast usually has some air voids present between them. A shrinkage up to 8% is permitted at the destination after verifying the ordered quantity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "How is the collection of Ballast done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) From Ballast depots",
            "b) Collection along the cess",
            "c) From ballast depot or along the cess",
            "d) From mine sites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ballast can be collected from the ballast depot and transported to the site with the help of ballast trains. It can also be collected along the cess and putting it directly on the track.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Where is the stacking of ballast done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alongside the railway line",
            "b) In containers",
            "c) In specially built sheds",
            "d) Stored in the trucks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Appropriate number of zones are made alongside the railway track for stacking of ballast. All the stacks in each zone are serially numbered.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "In the collection of ballast along the cess, what are the materials passing through 6mm square mesh called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fine aggregates",
            "b) Dust",
            "c) Coarse aggregates",
            "d) Silicates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The materials passing through 6mm square mesh are classified as Dust. It should not be more than 1% in the total ballast material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "What are the methods of measurement of quantity of ballast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stack measurement",
            "b) Wagon measurement",
            "c) Stack or wagon measurement",
            "d) Line measurement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ballast is transported in wagons and stacked alongside the railway lines. Their quantity can be measured either in stack or in wagon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an unfavourable condition for the stacking of Ballast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plane ground",
            "b) Ground with good drainage",
            "c) Firm ground",
            "d) Hilly areas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stacking of ballast should be done in a plane, firm ground providing good drainage. In hilly areas stacking is difficult and hence height of stack can be less than 1m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Why is a white line painted in case of Wagon measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To indicate the level up to which ballast can be loaded",
            "b) Ballast should be filled up to half the level of that line",
            "c) To know the minimum level up to which ballast should be filled",
            "d) To calculate the empty space inside the wagon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A white line should be painted inside the wagon to specify the level up to which ballast can be loaded. This makes calculation of volume of ballast easier.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Which quantity should be painted outside the wagon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth up to which ballast is filled",
            "b) Volume of ballast in cubic metres",
            "c) Minimum size of Ballast",
            "d) Volume of whole wagon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On the outside of the truck the volume in cubic metres up to the white line should be painted. It should be painted on both sides of the wagon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Los Angeles machine is used for which of the following tests?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aggregate abrasion value",
            "b) Aggregate impact test",
            "c) Water absorption test",
            "d) Flakiness index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aggregate should have resistance to abrasion. The aggregate abrasion value is checked by using Los Angeles machine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "What is the diameter of the cylinder used for Aggregate impact value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75mm",
            "b) 75cm",
            "c) 75 inches",
            "d) 750cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ballast sample is oven dried and placed in a metal cylinder with 75mm diameter and 50mm depth. The ballast is duly tamped in different stages while placing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "What is the weight of the test hammer used for Aggregate impact value?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14kg",
            "b) 140 grams",
            "c) 20kg",
            "d) 1200 grams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Weight of the test hammer is about 14kg and it’s made to fall on the surface of the cylinder from a height of 380mm. The sample is subjected to 15 such blows.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Flakiness is the percentage by weight of particles with a least dimension less than ________ of their mean dimension.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three-fifth",
            "b) Two-third",
            "c) Three-fourth",
            "d) Two-fifth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flakiness index of an aggregate is defined as the percentage by weight of particles with least dimensions less than three fifths of mean dimension. Size smaller than 6.3mm are not suitable for test.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "What is the temperature for oven drying of aggregates for Specific gravity and water absorption test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50-60°C",
            "b) 100-110°C",
            "c) 27-32°C",
            "d) 130-140°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Weight of saturated aggregates in water, saturated dry aggregates in air and oven dried aggregates in air is taken for calculation of specific gravity and water absorption of aggregates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "The side slopes of embankment and cutting depend upon which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear strength of soil",
            "b) Angle of repose of soil",
            "c) Shear strength and angle of repose of soil",
            "d) The loading on embankment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A particular slope is provided to the embankment and the cutting. This side slope depends upon the shear strength as well as the angle of repose of the soil.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "What is slip circle method used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To determine the stability of the slope",
            "b) To determine permeability of soil",
            "c) For calculation of slope value",
            "d) To measure the slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Huge amount of load acts on the tracks which gets transferred to the formation. The slope of the formation must be stable to bear it. The stability of this slope is determined by slip circle method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "Why are the slopes turfed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To prevent erosion of side slope",
            "b) To erode side slopes",
            "c) To distribute load properly",
            "d) For bearing load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of rain water the side slope might get eroded. A thin layer of cohesive soil is thus used to prevent erosion by this arrangement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true in case of Black cotton soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) During dry season ballast penetrates into cracks",
            "b) It becomes soft during rainy season",
            "c) It gains strength with addition of water",
            "d) Loss in moisture content results in cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Black cotton soil changes its properties with change in moisture content. It loses its strength with addition of water. It has an undesirable property of swelling and shrinkage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "What can be the use of a bituminous carpet in Black cotton soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To stop the surface water from reaching the formation",
            "b) To add lime to the surface",
            "c) Helps in compaction",
            "d) To keep it warm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Surface water on reaching the formation can make it wet and result in swelling. Thus a bituminous carpet is provided for its protection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "What should be the value of cross slope for embankments in other than good soils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 50",
            "b) 1 in 40",
            "c) 1 in 30",
            "d) 1 in 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For good drainage cross slope should be provided. In other than good soils, a cross slope of 1 in 30 from centre towards the cess should be provided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "What is the effect of excess of water in the subgrade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in shear strength",
            "b) Reduction in bearing capacity",
            "c) Reduction in bearing capacity and shear strength",
            "d)Reduction in moisture content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Firstly soil samples are taken from the site. Then they are classified as ‘good’ or ’other than good’ based on their grain size as well as their consistency limits.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "What should be the maximum percentage of plastic fines present in non-cohesive material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 33%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fines are the particles measuring up to 75mm. in sand, gravel, and other non-cohesive materials they should not exceed more than 5% value.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "What should be the maximum liquid limit value for Macadam type materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 55",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For Macadam type materials liquid limit should not exceed 35 and plasticity limit should be less than 10. The coefficient of uniformity should be above 4.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expression for calculation of Coefficient of curvature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) D30/D60 × D10",
            "b) D230/D60 × D10",
            "c) D30/D60 × D40",
            "d) D230/D40 × D10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coefficient of curvature can be calculated by the expression D230/D60 × D10. Its value for Macadam materials should be between 1 and 3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which test is used for determining the dry density of the material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proctor’s test",
            "b) Blain’s test",
            "c) Vicat’s test",
            "d) Alexander’s test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compaction of Macadam should be done near the optimum moisture content to achieve at least 90% of the maximum dry density which is determined by Proctor’s test.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be a reason for Failure of Natural Ground?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear Failure",
            "b) Excessive settlement",
            "c) Shear failure or excessive settlement",
            "d) Less settlement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Reason for Failure of natural ground can be either Shear failure or excessive settlement. Shear failure usually happens when construction is going on or instantly after construction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "How does the provision of sand drains in natural ground affects its load carrying capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helps in quicker consolidation",
            "b) Increases the load",
            "c) Checks shear failure",
            "d) Checks its heaving tendency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Providing sand drains help in quicker consolidation of the natural ground thus increasing its load bearing capacity. Provision of suitably spaced sheet or balancing embankment are other methods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "What is a slip passing below the toe of bank through its base known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toe failure",
            "b) Base failure",
            "c) Slope failure",
            "d) Embankment failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Shear failure of the embankment occurs generally due to slip or weight of embankment or moving load on it. The forces which resist the failure are cohesion and internal friction of fill material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of providing an inverted filter blanket?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To improve the drainage",
            "b) To improve the bearing capacity of soil",
            "c) To make the track resilient",
            "d) To improve drainage and bearing capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A slip passing below the toe of bank through its base known as Base failure. A slip passing through toe of bank is called toe failure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is wrong regarding the cement grouting of embankments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It prevents water from flowing into the subgrade",
            "b) Cement and sand are used in the ratio of 1:8 to 1:10",
            "c) Its done under a pressure of 60psi",
            "d) The soil is stabilised"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An inverted filter blanket aids as an obstruction for the upward movement of clay. It also offers a porous medium to drain off the surface water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Geotextiles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are made up of Polymers",
            "b) They allow water and soil fines to pass",
            "c) They allow water to pass through",
            "d) It stabilises soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cement grouting under a pressure helps stabilising the soil and prevents water from flowing into the subgrade. Cement and sand are used in the ratio of 1:2 to 1:6.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not included in the data regarding the history of the affected section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Method of Construction",
            "b) Date of opening to Traffic",
            "c) Drainage conditions",
            "d) Speed restrictions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For determining the type of treatment various data has to be collected. History of affected section does not include drainage conditions. It is included in ‘Site details’.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "What is obtained to get an idea of the Track maintainability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of visits to track",
            "b) Site details",
            "c) Ballast penetration profiles",
            "d) History of affected section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For an idea of the track maintainability, the man days utilised for maintenance per kilometre should be determined. The number of track visits for the last five years should be obtained.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "What can be done to reduce creep of soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing turfing",
            "b) Providing mats",
            "c) Providing side berms",
            "d) Cement grouting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Providing turfing or mats can be done in case of erosion of Banks. To reduce creeping of soil, flattening of slopes or provision of side berms is adopted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "What can be the remedial measure adopted for track level variations due to inadequate drainage due to high cess?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improving side drainage by lowering the cess",
            "b) Treatment with lime slurry pressure injection",
            "c) Cement grouting",
            "d) Cationic bituminous emulsion below ballast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For tack level variations due to inadequate drainage due to high cess, we can improve side drainage by lowering the cess and screening the ballast. We use lime slurry injection when there is seasonal variation in moisture content of top formation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "What is the function of Fish plates in a track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joining rail to wooden sleepers",
            "b) Joining rail to cast iron sleepers",
            "c) Joining rail to steel trough sleepers",
            "d) Joining rail to rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The function of Fish plates is to hold two rails together. It restricts the movement of rails in horizontal and vertical planes. Combination of Fish plates, nuts and bolts are used for this purpose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "In the steel used to manufacture fish plates what should be the composition of manganese?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exactly 0.6%",
            "b) Less than 0.8%",
            "c) Not more than 0.6%",
            "d) More than 0.6%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The steel used to make fish plates are special and should not contain manganese and silicon more than 0.6% and 0.15% respectively. Carbon content should be in the range of 0.3-0.42%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "The strength of fish plates are _______ as the rail section.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roughly same",
            "b) Almost double",
            "c) Almost half",
            "d) Roughly half"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fish plates are so designed that their strength is almost equal to that of the rail section. Also, their sectional area is same as that of the rail section.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Why are Combination fish plates used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To connect rails of two different sections",
            "b) To connect two different fastenings",
            "c) To increase load",
            "d) To connect two rails of similar sections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Combination fish plates are also called Junction fish plates. They are used to connect rails which have two different sections.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "What are dog spikes used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixing sleepers to rails",
            "b) Fixing rails to steel sleepers",
            "c) Fixing rails wooden sleepers",
            "d) Fixing sleepers to ballast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Because the head of this spike looks like a dog’s ear, it is called as Dog spike. It is used for fixing rails to wooden sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "What is the correct number of dog spikes used on a curved track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 outside and 1 inside",
            "b) 1 on either side",
            "c) 2 outside and 2 inside",
            "d) 2 outside and 1 inside"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On a straight track, 1 spike on either side is used. On a curved track, 2 outside and 1 inside is required. In bridges and joint sleepers the dog spikes used are 2 outside and 2 inside.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "What else is used along with Round spikes for fixing rails to sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dog spikes",
            "b) Anti creep bearing plates",
            "c) Double spikes",
            "d) Wooden joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For fixing rails to sleepers, round spikes in addition to anti creep bearing plates are used. Diameter of the round spike is almost 18mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "What type of fittings are used for fastening slide chairs to the sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fang bolts",
            "b) Round spikes",
            "c) Screw spikes",
            "d) Dog spikes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fang bolts are used for fastening slide chairs to sleepers. Round spikes, Dog spikes and Screw spikes are used for fixing rails to sleepers. Round spikes are also used for fixing switches onto wooden sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "What is the diameter of rail screws?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15mm",
            "b) 22mm",
            "c) 20mm",
            "d) 25mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Screw spikes having 20mm diameter are called plate screws. The screw spikes having diameter of 22mm are called as Rail screws.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Which of the following bearing plates require a spring key?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Special CI bearing plates",
            "b) Cast iron anti creep plates",
            "c) Flat MS bearing plates",
            "d) MS canted bearing plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If Bull headed rails are to be fixed using special cast iron bearing plates, a spring key is used. Spring key is required to keep the rail in position.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "What is the value of cant provided in Mild steel canted bearing plates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 30",
            "b) 1 in 40",
            "c) 1 in 20",
            "d) 1 in 35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mild steel canted bearing plates are used on joints and curves. They provide better bearing area to the rails and have a cant of 1 in 20.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "What was the disadvantage of older type of trough sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They were heavy",
            "b) They used to get deformed easily",
            "c) They were very costly",
            "d) They didn’t serve the purpose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of the provision of pressed up lugs in the older type of trough sleepers, they used to get cracked or damaged easily. Spring steel loose jaws are used to solve this problem.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Two way keys are not used for fixing which of the following sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CST-9 sleepers",
            "b) Wooden sleepers",
            "c) Pot sleepers",
            "d) Trough sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Two way key has a two way taper provided at both the ends and it can be driven in both the direction. It is used for fixing CST-9, Pot and Trough sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong regarding rubber coated fish plates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They were used at insulated joints",
            "b) They had limited life",
            "c) They are better than epoxy coated fish plates",
            "d) They get damaged early in service"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rubber coated fish plates were found to get easily damaged during tests and thus had limited service life. Now epoxy fish plates are being tried.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Which of the following liner is used to overcome the problem of holes in trough sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anderson liner",
            "b) Mota Singh liner",
            "c) Loose jaw liner",
            "d) Trough liner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of continuous moving of loads, wear and tear of the holes in the tough sleeper takes place. This makes them elongated and this problem is dealt by using Mota Singh liner.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a cotter used on Indian Railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centre split cotter",
            "b) Side split cotter",
            "c) Solid end split cotter",
            "d) Empty end split cotter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cotters are used for fixing tie bars to CI sleepers. They are classified based on their methods of splitting. The four types of cotters used on Indian railways are; Centre split, Side split, Solid end split and Bent plate split cotter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Cotters and tie bars are used to fix rails to _____ sleepers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) concrete",
            "b) cast Iron",
            "c) mild steel",
            "d) wooden"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answers: b\nExplanation: Cotters are used to fix tie bars to Cast Iron sleepers. The rails are then fixed onto the sleepers. For wooden sleepers, spikes, screws or bearing plates are used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "MS tie bars are used for holding two plates of ______ sleepers together.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CST-9",
            "b) wooden",
            "c) steel trough",
            "d) cast Iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two plates of CST-9 sleepers are held together with the help of MS tie bars. Length of the tie bar is 2720mm and section is 50mm x 13mm for Broad Gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Which clips are most widely used with concrete sleepers on Indian Railways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pandrol clips",
            "b) Spring steel clips",
            "c) Round spikes",
            "d) Bearing plates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pandrol clips are also called as elastic rail clips. They can be fixed on different types of sleepers (like concrete, cast iron) with the help of a base plate. They require very less maintenance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Pandrol clips?",
        "Options": [
            "a) No usage of adjustment gauge possible",
            "b) It provides safeguard from theft",
            "c) They are most widely used on concrete sleepers",
            "d) It gets caught inside MCI insert"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pandrol clips do not provide safeguard from theft or sabotage and thus get stolen easily. They can be taken out from the fitting easily with the help of a Hammer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "What should be the range for the Brinel Hardness Number of the IRN 202 clip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120-240",
            "b) 240-375",
            "c) 375-415",
            "d) 450-500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The clip is treated so as to keep the Brinel Hardness Number in the range of 375-415. The whole arrangement is so made that it should handle a load of 1000kg and deflection of 18.5mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a drawback of the IRN 202 clip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is costly and bulky",
            "b) It requires frequent maintenance",
            "c) Corrosion of heel can lead to development cracks",
            "d) Rail changing is very difficult"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Changing of rail is easy in case of IRN 202 clips. The rail can be changed by removing the fastening only by relaxing the bolt and pushing the rail out.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Among which of the following fastenings permits the interchanging of 52kg rails with 60kg rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Herbert Meir",
            "b) ERC MK-III",
            "c) Spring steel clip",
            "d) Lock spikes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HM fastenings consist of four coach screws. A rubber pad which is grooved is placed under the seat to provide resistance to lateral movement of rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "For which type of concrete sleepers Stem type MCI is used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Post tension concrete",
            "b) Pre tension concrete",
            "c) Post compression concrete",
            "d) Pre compression concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stem type MCI inserts are used in pre tension concrete sleepers. Gate type MCI inserts are used in post tension concrete sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which among the following is used between rails and sleepers to absorb shocks, resist lateral movement of rails and provide electrical insulation between rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spring steel clips",
            "b) CI anti creep bearing plate",
            "c) Rubber pads",
            "d) Spring steel loose jaw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rubber pad is provided between rails and sleepers. Spring steel is an elastic fastening. CI anti creep bearing plates and spring loose jaws are used as fastenings in wooden and steel trough sleepers respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be present in the composite liners developed by the RDSO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Malleable cast iron",
            "b) Mild Steel",
            "c) Malleable cast iron or Mild Steel",
            "d) Concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two types of composite liners are developed by the RDSO. One is with malleable cast iron and nylon components and second composite liner with MS and nylon components.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "What is the reason behind the breaking of GFN-66 liners?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rusting of rail surface",
            "b) Uneven seating",
            "c) Rusting of rail surface and uneven seating",
            "d) Improper design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: GFN-66 liners have high chances of breaking when they are fitted with ERC clip assembly on concrete sleepers. The primary reasons are uneven seating and rusting of rail surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "What is an elastic fastening called which is easy to fit in but difficult to remove?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pilfer proof elastic fastening",
            "b) Proof elastic fastening",
            "c) Circlip proof elastic fastening",
            "d) Pandrol clip elastic fastening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pilfer proof elastic fastening is easy to fit in the arrangement but cannot be removed effortlessly without causing damage to the assembly. The design of this fastening consists of a fitting called pilfer proof circlip.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "Why are fastenings tested in the laboratory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To check their rigidity",
            "b) To calculate traffic density",
            "c) To check their suitability in the field",
            "d) To see their breaking point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Before actually using the rigid and elastic fastenings on field they are first tested in laboratory to check their suitability. Vibrogir and pulsator are used for this purpose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Why is Vibrogir used in Laboratories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To apply pressure on rails",
            "b) To check effectiveness of rail",
            "c) To check effectiveness of fastenings",
            "d) To check rigidity of rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: High frequency vibrations are produced with the help of this equipment. By simulating similar field conditions by this equipment, the effectiveness of the fastenings is checked.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "What are the extra activities performed by the pulsator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Applies lateral pressure on the rail fastening",
            "b) Applies vertical pressure on the rail fastening",
            "c) Applies longitudinal pressure on the rail fastening",
            "d) Applies lateral and vertical pressure on the rail fastening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The vibrogir produces vibrations to check effectiveness. The pulsator in addition to this also applies lateral and vertical pressure on the rail fastening.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "According to wave motion theory what causes creep of rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moving loads",
            "b) Stationary loads",
            "c) Faulty rails",
            "d) Poor maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of moving loads the rails deflect. As the wheel moves ahead the depression also moves with it. This wave motion makes the rail move forward with the moving loads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "What causes creep in rails according to Percussion theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Moving loads",
            "b) Impact of wheels at rail end",
            "c) Faulty arrangements",
            "d) Manufacturing defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Percussion theory when wheels move from one rail to another they push the rail at the joint. This makes it move longitudinally and causes creep.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which theory states the formation of creep because of backward thrust?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drag theory",
            "b) Percussion theory",
            "c) Moving loads theory",
            "d) Joint rail theory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to drag theory the driving wheels of locomotive push the rail backwards. The other wheels push the rail in direction of motion. This results in movement of rails causing creep.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "How is creep caused because of Starting operation of locomotive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because of backward thrust",
            "b) Forward pushing of rail",
            "c) Expansion of rail",
            "d) Contraction of rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of starting or acceleration of train the backward thrust created by its wheels tend to push the rail backwards. This is responsible for causing creep of rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "In which direction creep is developed in double line section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Opposite to the direction of Traffic",
            "b) In the direction if Traffic",
            "c) In both directions",
            "d) Arbitrary direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Double line section is unidirectional. Trains on a track thus move in one direction only. This is the reason that develops creep in the direction of traffic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "How does limited quantities of ballast contribute to development of creep?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By offering limited ballast resistance",
            "b) By offering excess ballast resistance",
            "c) By increasing drainage",
            "d) Limited quantity of ballast helps in decreasing creep"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If limited quantity of Ballast is present on the track, insufficient ballast resistance is offered to the movement of sleepers. This causes the development of creep.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "What is the major effect of sleepers coming out of square due to creep?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unpleasant rides",
            "b) Increased stresses",
            "c) More expansion",
            "d) Less load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of creep sleepers come out of square. This results in effect on the gauge and alignment of the track. This leads to unpleasant rides.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "What is the effect of creep on expansion gaps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They get widen at all places",
            "b) They get close at all places",
            "c) They get widen at some and close at other places",
            "d) They are not affected due to creep"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Because of creep, the expansion joints get close at some places and widen at others. The joints thus get jammed and huge stresses are developed in fish plates and bolts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong regarding the effect of Creep?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interlocking gets disturbed",
            "b) Possibility of Buckling",
            "c) Eases the changing of rails",
            "d) Sleepers move out of square"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Excessive creep makes the changing of rail very difficult. This happens because the new rail is found to be either too long or too short because of creep.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Which of the following device is used for the measurement of creep?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Creep measurer",
            "b) Creep indicator",
            "c) Rail Creep finder",
            "d) Creep posts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For measurement of creep a device called Creep indicator is used. It has two creep posts. Creep posts are generally rail pieces used on either side of the track.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "The top level of creep post is generally at what level as compared to the rail level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) About half the height of rail",
            "b) Same as the rail level",
            "c) 2 inches higher than the rail level",
            "d) 2 inches lower than the rail level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The top level of creep post is same as that of the rail level. This ensures ease in measurement of creep which is done using a fishing string.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "What is the maximum value of creep permissible in any track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300mm",
            "b) 50mm",
            "c) 150mm",
            "d) 200mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any track should not have creep more than 150mm (6 inches). But in case of tracks approaching points and crossings there should be no creep.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "For the adjustment of creep what type of survey is conducted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Survey of Ballast quantity",
            "b) Survey of expansion gaps",
            "c) Survey of lateral load",
            "d) Gradient survey"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For adjustment of creep, firstly we need to know the number of expansion gaps. Thus a survey regarding the expansion gaps and position of rail joints is carried out.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "In pulling back of rails how many rails can be dealt with at a time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At least 5",
            "b) Not more than 5",
            "c) Only one",
            "d) Two rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the adjustment of creep fish plates from one side are removed and the other end fish pates are loosened. Spikes are also removed or loosened.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Where is the creep adjuster placed on the track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the middle",
            "b) On the joint",
            "c) Between the joint and the mid-point",
            "d) Anywhere on the track"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rails are long and heavy. Huge manpower is required for this purpose. Thus rails are pulled one by one and is a slow process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "How are the gaps closed by using the creep adjuster?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By pulling the rail backwards",
            "b) By pushing the rail forward",
            "c) By lifting up the rail",
            "d) By cutting the rail short"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Creep adjuster is generally used when excessive work is involved. It is placed at the middle of the track with wide and jammed joints behind and ahead of it respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "What happens when the operation leaves some of the expansion gaps too wide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are left forever",
            "b) They are filled with some material",
            "c) They are tackled in the next position",
            "d) A piece of rail is inserted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The gaps are closed using the creep adjuster by pushing the rails forward. A gap of few inches is left behind among the rail ends in opposite direction of the adjuster.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Which of the following locations of Track is least susceptible to creep?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dip in stretches with long gradients",
            "b) Point where steel sleeper track meets a wooden sleeper track",
            "c) Point where steel sleeper track meets a CST-9 sleeper track",
            "d) Point where CST-9 sleeper track meets a wooden sleeper track"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The corrected rails are fastened with keys and then the rails on other side are tackled. The expansion gap which is too wide if left, it is tackled in the next position of the creep adjuster.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Which of the following device is used for the measurement of creep?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Creep measurer",
            "b) Creep indicator",
            "c) Rail Creep finder",
            "d) Creep posts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For measurement of creep a device called Creep indicator is used. It has two creep posts. Creep posts are generally rail pieces used on either side of the track.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "The top level of creep post is generally at what level as compared to the rail level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) About half the height of rail",
            "b) Same as the rail level",
            "c) 2 inches higher than the rail level",
            "d) 2 inches lower than the rail level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The top level of creep post is same as that of the rail level. This ensures ease in measurement of creep which is done using a fishing string.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "What is the maximum value of creep permissible in any track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300mm",
            "b) 50mm",
            "c) 150mm",
            "d) 200mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Any track should not have creep more than 150mm (6 inches). But in case of tracks approaching points and crossings there should be no creep.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "What is a gradient in which track loses elevation in direction of movement of traffic called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ruling gradient",
            "b) Falling gradient",
            "c) Rising gradient",
            "d) Level gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gradients are provided so that the rise or fall in the track’s path can be easily traversed. A down gradient also called as falling gradient is the one in which drop of elevation in the direction of movement is recorded.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "What is the meaning of a gradient represented as 1 in 400?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A rise of 1m in 400m",
            "b) Rise of 400m in 1km",
            "c) A 400% rise in track",
            "d) A 1m rise in 4km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gradient is represented as the distance travelled for a rise or fall of 1 unit distance. 1 in 400 means a rise of 1m is recorded after travelling 400m. 1 in 400 is also represented as 0.25%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which gradient determines the maximum load that can be hauled by a locomotive on that section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rising gradient",
            "b) Falling gradient",
            "c) Ruling gradient",
            "d) Momentum gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ruling gradient is the steepest gradient that is present in the entire section. It determines the maximum load that can be carried by the section. The power of locomotive should also be considered while deciding this gradient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "What is the range for ruling gradient adopted by the Indian railways in hilly terrain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 100 to 1 in 200",
            "b) 1 in 100 to 1 in 150",
            "c) 1 in 150 to 1 in 250",
            "d) 1 in 250 to 1 in 300"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ruling gradient adopted by the Indian railways in hilly terrain can be from 1 in 100 to 1 in 150.  For plain terrain it can be from 1 in 150 to 1 in 250.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "What is Pusher gradient also known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Friction gradient",
            "b) Helper gradient",
            "c) Momentum gradient",
            "d) Ruling gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pusher gradients can sometimes be steeper than Ruling gradient. If one locomotive is not sufficient to pull the entire load, another locomotive or engine can be used. It is also known as Helper gradient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct about Momentum gradient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A falling gradient is followed by a rising gradient",
            "b) It is not steeper than the Ruling gradient",
            "c) It requires an extra engine",
            "d) It is very flat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Momentum gradient is steeper than the Ruling gradient. When a train travels on a falling gradient it gains momentum and can travels on the rising gradient which might be steeper than the Ruling gradient.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "What is the reason of compensation of Gradient on curves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are very difficult to design",
            "b) They are uneconomical",
            "c) Curves provide extra resistance",
            "d) They are dangerous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gradients in station yard are usually flat to prevent standing vehicles from moving away from the yard. But a certain gradient is essential for ensuring proper drainage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "What is the value of Grade compensation on Broad Gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.04% per degree of curve",
            "b) 70/R, where R is the radius of curve",
            "c) 0.04% per degree of curve or 70/R whichever is minimum",
            "d) 0.03% per degree of curve or 35/R whichever is minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On curves the locomotive experiences extra resistance to its movement. Thus gradients on a curve should be flatter because more resistance can cause uncomfortable journey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Find the steepest gradient on a 3 degree curve for a BG line with ruling gradient of 1 in 200.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 200",
            "b) 1 in 432",
            "c) 1 in 284",
            "d) 1 in 263"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gradient compensation for BG is 0.04% per degree of curve or 70/R whichever is minimum. For MG it is 0.03% per degree of curve or 52.5/R whichever is minimum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Degree of curve is the angle subtended at its centre by a _______ chord.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30.5ft",
            "b) 100m",
            "c) 30.5cm",
            "d) 100ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A curve is defined by its radius or by its degree. The degree of curve is the angle subtended at the curve’s centre by a 100ft or 30.5m chord.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for the degree of curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1750/R",
            "b) 3500/R",
            "c) 5370/R",
            "d) 2000/R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angle subtended by a 30.5m chord or degree of curve is given as 360°x30.5/2πR. This when simplified is equal to 1750/R, where R is in metres.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "The maximum permissible degree of a curve on a track does not depend on which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gauge",
            "b) Wheel base",
            "c) Maximum Permissible superelevation",
            "d) Speed of train"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum permissible degree of curve on a track is determined by factors like gauge, wheel base and maximum permissible superelevation. After this the permissible speed of the train on track is determined.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "According to Tangential offset method which of the following is the correct relation between offset and length of chord?",
        "Options": [
            "a) On = Cn2/4R",
            "b) On = Cn2/2R",
            "c) On = Cn2/6R",
            "d) On = Cn2/R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When we have to set out a short curve of length of around 100m, Tangential offset method can be used. The relation between offset and length of chord can be given as On = Cn2 /2R.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "In Long chord offset method, how is the Versine V is calculated from long chord?",
        "Options": [
            "a) V = C2/πR",
            "b) V = C2/8R",
            "c) V = C2/5R",
            "d) V = C2/18R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Versine is calculated as V = C2/8R, where C is the length of the long chord. The long chord is divided into 8 parts and then values of perpendicular offsets are calculated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as Rankine’s method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chord deflection method",
            "b) Versine method",
            "c) Theodolite method",
            "d) Long chord offset method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Theodolite method is also known as Rankine’s method. It is particularly used when high accuracy is required. Curve is set with the help of Theodolite and a chain or tape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "What is the definition of Superelevation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference in height between outer and inner rail",
            "b) Height difference from outer rail to centre of track",
            "c) Height difference from inner rail to centre of track",
            "d) Slope at which rail is laid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Superelevation or cant is the difference in height between outer and inner rail on a curve. The outer rail is gradually lifted above the inner rail to provide this.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as another name of inner rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slope rail",
            "b) Fixed rail",
            "c) Gradient rail",
            "d) Cant rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inner rail is also known as Gradient rail. It is taken as reference rail while determining superelevation and is normally maintained at its original level.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "In case of equilibrium speed what is the angle between resultant of weight and radial acceleration and plane of rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are perpendicular",
            "b) Inclined at 45°",
            "c) Tangential",
            "d) Between 45° and 90°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Equilibrium speed is when the effect of centrifugal force is completely balanced by the cant provided. The resultant of weight and radial acceleration is perpendicular to plane of rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "What should be done if maximum permissible speed is less than maximum sectional speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More cant should be given",
            "b) Another Curve should be inserted",
            "c) Permanent speed restrictions should be implemented",
            "d) No alterations should be made"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Maximum permissible speed is the highest speed at which a train is permitted to travel on a curve. If it is less than maximum sectional speed, permanent speed restrictions should be imposed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "Which of the following occurs when train travels at a speed greater than equilibrium speed on a curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cant deficiency",
            "b) Cant excess",
            "c) Cant gradient",
            "d) Rate gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cant deficiency is the difference between theoretical cant required and the actual cant provided. When train travels at a speed lesser than equilibrium speed on a curve cant excess occurs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for equilibrium superelevation in millimetres?",
        "Options": [
            "a) e = GV2/254R",
            "b) e = GV2/381R",
            "c) e = GV2/127R",
            "d) e = GV2/96R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Equilibrium superelevation, e = F x G/W\n                                                                             = W/g x V2/R x G/W\n                                                                             = GV2/gR\ne = GV2/127R in millimetres.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "A per the prescribed value, what should be the maximum value of cant excess on Broad gauge?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 65mm",
            "b) 75mm",
            "c) 92mm",
            "d) 100mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The superelevation to be provided also depends on the average speed of the goods traffic moving on the section. This is done to make sure that slow trains move safely without any chances of derailment due to excess cant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which formula was used earlier for the calculation of Safe speed on curves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Martin’s Formula",
            "b) Henry’s equation",
            "c) Bolt’s formula",
            "d) Anderson’s formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Safe speed is the one which protects a carriage from overturning and derailment. Earlier Martin’s formula V = 4.4(R-70)1/2, was used for its calculation on Transitioned curves.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct revised formula for the calculation of speed at transitioned curves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) V = 0.27((Ca + Cd) x R)1/2",
            "b) V = 0.347((Ca + Cd) x R)1/2",
            "c) V = 0.27((Ca + Cd) x R)1/4",
            "d) V = 0.27((Ca + Cd) x R)1/3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Martin’s formula which was earlier used was changed by applying some formula based on some theoretical considerations. The revised formula for BG is V = 0.27((Ca + Cd) x R)1/2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "Calculate the super elevation for a 2° curve for equilibrium speed of 80kmph.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 146.3mm",
            "b) 214mm",
            "c) 100.8mm",
            "d) 78.5mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: G = 1750mm, V = 80km/h\n                      R = 1750/2 = 875\n                        Super elevation = GV2/127R\n                        = 1750×802/127×875\n                        = 100.8mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "On which portion of the track is a Transition curve provided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between straight line and circular curve",
            "b) Before straight line",
            "c) On one side of circular curve",
            "d) In the middle of circular curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transition curve is placed in between a straight line and circular curve on both sides. It is provided so that sudden centrifugal force should not come into effect while moving from straight track to circular one.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Which of the following is wrong about Transition curves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Degree of curvature is uniform throughout its length",
            "b) Radius of curvature decreases from a specified value to zero",
            "c) Gradual increase in superelevation from zero",
            "d) Should ensure a gradual increase or decrease in centrifugal forces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In transition curve the radius of curvature decreases gradually from infinity at the straight line to a desired value at the circular curve. Superelevation increases from zero to specified value.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "What is the correct formula of shift?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S = L2 / 24R",
            "b) S = L2 / 2R",
            "c) S = L2 / 4R",
            "d) S = L2 / 24R2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main curve to be fit in the transition curve is moved inward by shift which is calculated as S = L2 / 24R. Here, L is the length of transition curve in metre.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct in case of an S-shaped transition curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curvature assumes shape of quadratic parabola",
            "b) Shift required is twice",
            "c) Gradient is at centre and twice steeper",
            "d) Desirable when shift is restricted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An S-shaped transition curve is desirable when shift is restricted. In this case shift required is half of the shift provided in case of straight line ramp.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a formula used to calculate the length of a transition curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L = 0.008CaxVm",
            "b) L = 0.008CdxVm",
            "c) L = 0.72Ca",
            "d) L = 0.08CdxVmx S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Here Ca is the actual cant, Cd is the cant deficiency. The length of transition curve is taken as the maximum of the following formulae; L = 0.008Cd x Vm, L = 0.008Ca x Vm and L = 0.72Ca.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "How is a compound curve formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By a circular curve and straight line",
            "b) By 2 circular curves of same radii",
            "c) By 2 circular curves of different radii",
            "d) By more than 2 curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A compound curve is formed when two circular curves having different radii are combined. They have a common transition curve between them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Which curve is formed by the combination of 2 circular curves with opposite curvatures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compound curve",
            "b) Reverse curve",
            "c) Double circular curve",
            "d) Transition curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For calculating the Length of transition curve connecting two circular curves, firstly L=0.008(Ca1–Ca2)xV and L = (Cd1 – Cd2) x V are calculated. The greater among these is taken as the length of curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Why is the effect of curvature taken into consideration for providing extra clearance on curves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because of high speed of locomotive",
            "b) Because of rigid wheel base",
            "c) To easily move on gradients",
            "d) To accommodate more passengers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of the rigid structure of vehicle it does not follow the path of the curve. This is the reason for the requirement of extra clearance for the vehicle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The extra clearance required at centre of the vehicle which projects towards the inside of the curve is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overthrow",
            "b) End throw",
            "c) Side throw",
            "d) Stage throw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Overthrow is the extra clearance required at the centre of the vehicle which project towards the inside of the curve. It can be calculated by the equation, C2/8R.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "What is the formula for calculating the extra clearance required for leaning?",
        "Options": [
            "a) he/G",
            "b) 4he/G",
            "c) he/G2",
            "d) he/2G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On curves superelevation is provided to the tracks. Because of this the vehicle leans towards the inner edge of the curve creating a requirement for the extra clearance due to leaning.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "What is the value of the extra clearance on inside of the curve due to sway of vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal to clearance due to leaning",
            "b) Half of the clearance due to leaning",
            "c) one fourth of clearance due to leaning",
            "d) Twice of clearance due to leaning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vehicles experience additional sway on curves due to unbalanced forces caused by cant deficiency or excess. The extra clearance due to sway on inside of curve is one fourth of clearance due to leaning.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives the extra clearance outside the curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E2 – C2/8R",
            "b) E2 – C2/16R",
            "c) E – C/8R",
            "d) E – C/16R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Extra clearance which project towards the outside of the curve is called End throw. It is given by E2 – C2/8R. Here C is the centre to centre distance between bogies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "Which of the following clearances will not be taken into consideration for adjacent and curved Tracks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sway",
            "b) Lean",
            "c) Overthrow",
            "d) End throw"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Adjacent tracks on curves will have almost equal superelevation. Thus extra clearance due to lean will not be considered and Total clearance will be sum of Overthrow, sway and end throw.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "What is formed when 2 different gradients meet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Summit",
            "b) Sag",
            "c) Summit or Sag",
            "d) Another gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When 2 gradients meet an angle is formed at the point of contact. This angle formed is rough and can be smoothened by providing a curve called vertical curve which can be sag or summit curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following decides the length of Vertical curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradient of first curve",
            "b) Gradient of second curve",
            "c) Algebraic sum of gradients",
            "d) Algebraic difference of gradients"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Length of vertical curve depends upon the Algebraic difference of gradients. It also depends on the type of vertical curve, whether the curve is of sag or summit type.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "What should be the maximum rate of change of gradient in case of Summit curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1%",
            "b) 0.5%",
            "c) 0.3%",
            "d) 0.8%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In case of summit curve the rate of change of gradient should not exceed 0.1% between successive 100ft chords. In case of sag it should be 0.05%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct formula for finding the length of vertical curve for achieving maximum permissible speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) L = a/r x 30.5m",
            "b) L = r/a x 30.5m",
            "c) L = a/r x 100m",
            "d) L = r/a x 100m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The length of vertical curve for achieving maximum permissible speed is given by the formula L = a/r x 30.5m. Here ‘a’ is the percentage algebraic difference between gradients.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a major reason for the distortion of alignment of curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unbalanced loading on inner edge",
            "b) Horizontal forces on rail",
            "c) Unbalanced forces on outer edge",
            "d) Traffic from both sides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A rail curve is distorted because of unbalanced loading due to cant deficiency or cant excess and horizontal forces exerted on rails. These horizontal forces make the curve flatter and sharper at various locations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "According to cumulative frequency diagrams when should the realignment take place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cumulative percentage of versines is negligible",
            "b) Cumulative percentage of versines is between 10 and 50",
            "c) Cumulative percentage of versines is less than 80",
            "d) Cumulative percentage of versines is 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The versine variation on a 20m chord should be limited to 4 and 5mm for group A and B lines. Realignment should be taken up when the Cumulative percentage of versines which are lying within these limits is less than 80.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "What should be the maximum station to station variation of versine on curves where speed in excess of 100kmph are permitted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15mm",
            "b) 20mm",
            "c) 30mm",
            "d) 35mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Curves having speed permit of more than 100kmph should not have station to station variation of versines of more than 15mm. For speeds of 100kmph and less, this variation should not exceed 20mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Which is the formula for railexcess length which the inner rail gains over outer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4πG",
            "b) 2πG",
            "c) 4πG2",
            "d) πG"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The excess length which the inner rail gains over outer rail for a length L of the curve is the difference in circumference of outer and inner rail. It is given by 2πG, where G is the dynamic gauge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "Where are check rails provided on a track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perpendicular to the track",
            "b) Parallel to inner rail",
            "c) Parallel to outer rail",
            "d) On both the rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Check rails are provided parallel to the inner rail usually on sharp curves. This helps in reduction of lateral wear on the outer rail. They wear out quickly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "What is the minimum clearance prescribed for check rails for BG?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 44mm",
            "b) 120mm",
            "c) 18cm",
            "d) 18mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Check rails are provided on gauge face side of the inner rails especially on curves sharper than 8° on BG. Indian Railways has prescribed minimum clearance of 44mm for BG and MG routes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for diverting the rolling stock?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tongue rails",
            "b) Stock rail",
            "c) Turnout",
            "d) Check rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Turnout has a function of diverting the rolling stock from one track to another. It is basically an arrangement of points and crossings with lead rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "What is it called when a vehicle traverses on the switch from its thick end to thin end?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Right hand turnout",
            "b) Left hand turnout",
            "c) Facing direction",
            "d) Trailing direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the vehicle first negotiates a crossing and then traverse on a switch from its thick end to its thin end is called the Trailing direction. Turnout depends on the direction in which traffic is being diverted by it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of the following is another name for Tongue rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stock rail",
            "b) Switch rail",
            "c) Lead rail",
            "d) Toe rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tongue rail is a tapered and movable rail which is attached to a running at its thicker end. It is made up of high carbon or manganese steel to withstand wear and tear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "What is the thicker end of the Tongue rail called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toe",
            "b) Stock",
            "c) Lock",
            "d) Heel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The tongue rail needs to be fitted properly with the stock rail and thus is machined to very thin section. Tapered end of the tongue is called toe and thicker end is called heel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the correct types of switches?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stud and Sway switches",
            "b) Split and Swing switches",
            "c) Stud and Split switches",
            "d) Sway and Swing switches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: No separate tongue rail is provided in Stud type of switches. Split switches comprise of a pair of stock rails along with a pair of tongue rails.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "In which type of switches the tongue rail does not end at the heel of the switch?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fixed heel type",
            "b) Toe type",
            "c) Loose heel type",
            "d) Fixed and loose heel type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stud switches are no longer used on Indian Railways and are replaced by Split switches. Split switches are of two types – loose heel and fixed heel type.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Why are loose heel type switches not preferred?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because they use more number of Bolts",
            "b) Because they allow movement of tongue rail",
            "c) Because they make the structure weak",
            "d) They are difficult to operate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In fixed heel type switch the tongue rail does not end at heel of the switch. It extends further and is rigidly connected. In loose heel type the tongue rail finishes at the heel of the switch.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "In which toe of switches the switch rail kept 6mm higher than stock rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undercut switch",
            "b) Cut switch",
            "c) Overriding switch",
            "d) Single switch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To allow free movement of tongue rail all fish bolts in lead rail are tightened and those in tongue rail are kept loose. This discontinuity of the track at the heel makes the structure weak.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "Which of the following correctly defines the switch angle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Angle between gauge face of stock rail and tongue rail",
            "b) Angle between gauge face and check rail",
            "c) Angle between undercut switch and toe",
            "d) Angle between heel and toe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In overriding switches the switch rail is kept 6mm higher than the stock rail. This eradicates the possibility of splitting which can occur due to false flange moving in trailing direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "What is the distance between the gauge faces of tongue rail and stock rail called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Throw of switch",
            "b) Heel divergence",
            "c) Switch distance",
            "d) Flange way"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Switch angle is the angle between gauge face of stock rail and tongue rail at the theoretical toe of switch in closed position. It depends upon heel divergence and length of tongue rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "What is the major advantage of straight tongue rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easily manufactured",
            "b) Can be very long",
            "c) Very cheap",
            "d) They are light weighted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Heel divergence is made up of flange way clearance and the width of the tongue rail head that lies at the heel. Flange way clearance is the distance between attached faces of running rail and check rail at the nose of crossing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about length of tongue rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It varies with gauge and angle of switch",
            "b) Longer the length smoother is the entry to switch",
            "c) It should be less than length of the rigid wheel base",
            "d) Longer length occupies too much space"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tongue rails are of two types, straight and curves. Straight rails have the advantage of easy manufacturing and can be used for right hand and left hand turnout.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "What is done to ensure that at the wheel negotiates the gap of crossing properly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The wheel is widened",
            "b) Speed of train is increased",
            "c) A check rail is provided",
            "d) Material can be filled"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A gap is provided from the throw to the nose of the crossing and the flanged wheel jumps over it. The other wheel is guided with a check rail to ensure proper negotiation of gap by flanged wheel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "Which two rails are machined to form a nose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Point rail and Splice rail",
            "b) Check rail and Splice rail",
            "c) Point rail and Check rail",
            "d) Check rail and Toe rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Check rails do not form the nose. Point and Splice rail are machined to form a nose. Point rail ends at the nose and splice rail joins it a bit behind the nose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "What is the thickness of fine end of Point rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6mm",
            "b) 10mm",
            "c) 15mm",
            "d) 12mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Point rails, theoretically should be as thin as possible. But then they won’t be able to handle the load. Thus its fine end is cut slightly to form a blunt nose with 6mm thickness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Which type of crossing is formed when a right or left rail crosses a similar rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acute angle crossing",
            "b) Obtuse angle crossing",
            "c) Square crossing",
            "d) Any random crossing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Obtuse angle or diamond crossing is formed when two gauge faces meet at an obtuse angle. An obtuse crossing is formed when a right or left rail crosses a similar rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Built up crossing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is assembled with bolts and distance blocks",
            "b) Low initial cost",
            "c) Very Rigid",
            "d) Repairs can be done easily"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Built up crossing has advantages like low initial cost and easy repairs but they lack rigidity. The bolts require frequent checking and can break because of fast and heavy Traffic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of CMS crossing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less wear and tear",
            "b) Longer life",
            "c) Less initial cost",
            "d) Less maintenance cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cast steel crossing is a one piece crossing with no bolts. Because of this it is more rigid and requires very less maintenance. They have high initial cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "What type of crossing can be used when there is high speed traffic on main track and low speed on turnout track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Raised check crossing",
            "b) Position crossing",
            "c) CMS crossing",
            "d) Spring crossing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nowadays Cast Manganese Steel crossings are being preferred on Indian railways. They have long life, relatively lesser maintenance cost but high initial cost.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Which formula is used for the calculation of number of crossing based on Centre line method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2N = cot (α/2)",
            "b) N = cot (α/2)",
            "c) 2N = tan (α/2)",
            "d) N = tan (α/2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In centre line method, number of crossings N is measured along the centre line of the crossing. N can be calculated by 2N = cot (α/2). This method is used in USA and Britain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "What is another name of Coles method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isosceles method",
            "b) Right angle method",
            "c) Centre line method",
            "d) Back toe method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Coles method is also known as Right angle method. It is used on Indian Railways and N is measured along the base of a Right angled triangle. N = cot (α) is the formula used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "What is the limiting wear for a crossing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50mm",
            "b) 10mm",
            "c) 15mm",
            "d) 25mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A crossing is designated either by number of crossing or by the angle the gauge faces make with each other. All the three methods used to find N give different value according to the method adopted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "What is done for reconditioning of crossings at site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are hammered",
            "b) Gas welding",
            "c) Replacing the elements",
            "d) Filling of material in gaps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Limiting wear for crossing is 10mm and then it needs to be replaced. When the wear is around 6mm, reconditioning of the worn out sleeper is done.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for gas welding of crossings?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxyacetylene flame",
            "b) Methylene flame",
            "c) Nitrogen-carbon dioxide flame",
            "d) Ozone flame"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of tongue rail the limit of vertical wear for 52kg and 90R rails is 6mm. For lateral wear it is 8mm. Usually gas welding is adopted to recondition crossings at site.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "What is the distance from the tangent point to the heel of switch is called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Switch lead",
            "b) Curve lead",
            "c) Crossing lead",
            "d) Addition of curve lead and switch lead"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Distance measured along the line from tangent point to heel of switch is called switch lead. Curve lead is when distance is measured from tangent point to theoretical nose of crossing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct about heel divergence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is equal to lead of crossing",
            "b) It is the distance between main line and turnout",
            "c) It is the distance from tangent point to theoretical nose",
            "d) It is the addition of curve and switch lead"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Heel divergence is the distance between main line and turnout side at heel. While Lead of crossing is equal to the value obtained by subtracting switch lead from curve lead.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Which is the correct formula for calculation of Radius of Turnout?",
        "Options": [
            "a) R = 2R1 + G",
            "b) R = R1 + G",
            "c) R = R1 + 0.5G",
            "d) R = 3R1 + 2 G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Radius of turnout is equal to sum of Radius of centre line of turnout (R1) and half of Gauge width. R can sometimes be taken equal to R1, because of high value of radius of curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which type of chairs are used to provide a ramp to tongue rails?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grade off chairs",
            "b) Gauge tie chairs",
            "c) Slide chairs",
            "d) Stretcher bars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Grade off chairs are provided behind the heel of switches to give a ramp to the tongue rail. Slide chairs are used to help the tongue rails move laterally.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "What is used to prevent vertical movement between rail wing and nose of crossing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spherical washers",
            "b) Flat bearing plates",
            "c) Stretcher plates",
            "d) Distance blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Distance blocks with dishing fit surfaces are provided at the nose of the crossing to prevent vertical movement between rail wing and nose of crossing. Stretcher bars are provided to maintain the 2 tongue rails at an exact distance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "In Coles method from where does the curvature begin on the straight track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At the theoretical toe of switch",
            "b) At the actual toe of switch",
            "c) At theoretical nose of crossing",
            "d) At actual nose of crossing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coles method is used for designing a turnout taking off form a straight track. The curvature begins from the theoretical toe of switch and ends at the theoretical nose of crossing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "Which of the following formula is used for the calculation of curve lead in Coles method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curve lead = GN",
            "b) Curve lead = 2GN",
            "c) Curve lead = 3GN",
            "d) Curve lead = 7GN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Curve lead = G cotα + G cosecα\n                                            = GN + G (1 + N2)1/2      because cotα = N\n                                            = 2GN.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Which of the following represent the correct number and names of location of kinks in Coles method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At actual toe of switch and at heel of switch",
            "b) At heel of switch and theoretical nose of crossing",
            "c) At actual toe of switch, theoretical toe and heel of switch",
            "d) At actual toe of switch, heel of switch and at first distance block of crossing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tongue and wing rails are generally not curved and have three kinks. They are at the actual toe of switch, at heel of switch and at the first distance block of crossing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "What can be done to improve the speed of trains over turnouts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superelevation can be decreased",
            "b) Gaps can be kept gauge face and",
            "c) Curved switches can be provided",
            "d) Gauge can be decreased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The curve begins from the heel of the switch and ends at the toe of the crossing. No kink is experienced at point of crossing. Only one kink occurs which is at the toe of the switch.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of turnouts of European countries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Provision of transition curve between toe of switch and nose of crossing",
            "b) Long curves switches",
            "c) Low cant deficiency",
            "d) Curving of switches and crossings to same radius as lead curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: At turnouts, the vehicle sometimes cannot achieve good speed because of sudden change in direction of vehicle upon entry. Long curved switches can be provided to avoid this problem.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "What should be used for cleansing of slide chairs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Graphite",
            "b) Aluminium",
            "c) Oxyacetylene",
            "d) Brass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Condition of fittings should be proper and their timely maintenance should be done. Slide chairs should be cleansed and greased with Graphite. This helps in smooth operation of points.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "What is the maximum vertical wear permitted on wing rail?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6mm",
            "b) 8mm",
            "c) 10mm",
            "d) 15mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Maximum vertical wear should not be more than 10mm for wing rails and they should be renovated after wear of 6mm. For tongue rails maximum vertical wear permitted is 6mm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Which of the following locations is not to be checked for Gauge and cross level correctness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150mm behind the ANC",
            "b) 1m behind the ANC",
            "c) 300mm behind the ANC",
            "d) 1m ahead of the nose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gauge and cross level needs to be checked for their correctness for smooth journey. The locations at which they need to be checked include 150mm behind the ANC, 1m ahead of the nose and 1m behind the ANC on straight tracks and on turnouts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the weakest links in a track?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Joints",
            "b) Middle point of the track",
            "c) Tongue rails",
            "d) Highest point of curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The weakest link in a track is rail joint. There is a break in continuity of the rail at the joint because of presence of expansion gap and improper levels of rail heads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Why does the joint require frequent attention?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is of low quality",
            "b) It gets displaced easily",
            "c) They are of small size",
            "d) They are difficult to handle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Huge load acts upon the joint when train passes from one rail to another. Due to this the track geometry gets distorted and can cause accidents. To fix this the joints should be looked after frequently.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not associated with rail joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in noise effects",
            "b) Impact on quality",
            "c) Lesser fuel consumption",
            "d) Chances of sabotage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Because of presence of joints, there are effects like noise pollution, sabotaging chances and excessive wear of track components. The train requires extra efforts to haul itself over these joints which leads to increase in fuel consumption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "How much should be the strength of a rail joint?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Equal to the rail",
            "b) Half of the rail",
            "c) Equal to the weight of the train",
            "d) Double the rail strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A rail joint will be called an ideal joint if its strength is equal to the strength of the parent rail. Also, an ideal rail is the one having same stiffness as the parent rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Why is it necessary for the joint to hold the rail ends together?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To provide continuity",
            "b) To make the joint rigid",
            "c) To increase the cost",
            "d) To make it inelastic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rail joint should be elastic and flexible. The rails should be held together to keep the track continuous. This helps in avoiding wheel jumping or deviation of wheel from its original path.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Which of the following joint is not classified according to position of sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Supported joint",
            "b) Suspended joint",
            "c) Bridge joint",
            "d) Square joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rail joints can be classified based on position of sleepers or position of joints. According to position of sleepers, the joints are Supported joints, Suspended joints and Bridge joints. Square joint is joint classified based on position of joints.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements regarding supported joints is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rails are supported on sleepers",
            "b) No wear and tear",
            "c) No cantilever action",
            "d) Duplex sleeper is a type of supported joint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Supported joints have no cantilever action, but it does not reduce the wear and tear of the rails. Wear and tear of rails as well as sleepers occur and poses a problem for their maintenance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used in case of Bridge joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal flat",
            "b) Bridge plate",
            "c) Metal flat or Bridge plate",
            "d) Extra sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sleepers on either side of a bridge joint are connected. For this purpose a metal flat or a corrugated plate also known as a Bridge plate is used. These joints are generally not used on Indian Railways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "How are the joints in rails located in Square joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exactly opposite to each other",
            "b) ln a staggered manner",
            "c) Distance of 10m on one rail and 7m at other",
            "d) Can be arranged according requirement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Joints can be classified as Square and Staggered joints based on their position. In square joints their location is exactly opposite on each rail. Square joints are most commonly used on Indian Railways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not correct regarding Gas Pressure Welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is costlier than Flash butt welding",
            "b) Heat is produced by combination of oxygen and acetylene gas",
            "c) Welding happens by fusion of the melted metals",
            "d) Stationary and mobile units are available for gas pressure welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In gas pressure welding necessary heat is produced by combination of oxygen and acetylene gases. This method is cheaper than flash butt welding and the quality of welding is also good.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Scheron process is used in which of the following welding methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas welding",
            "b) Flash butt welding",
            "c) Metal arc welding",
            "d) Thermit welding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A high voltage source is used for energising a metal electrode which is then brought near another metal object. Heat is generated causing the two ends to weld. This type of welding can be done by using Insert plate technique, Scheron process or enclosed space technique.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the components of the Thermit mixture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium and steel",
            "b) Aluminium and iron oxide",
            "c) Magnesium and iron oxide",
            "d) Silicon and Aluminium oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A mixture of iron oxide and finely divided aluminium is used to form the Thermit mixture. It is then ignited and heat is generated producing aluminium oxide and iron.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true about Flash butt welding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electric resistance produces heat",
            "b) It has two movable jaws",
            "c) It is the standard method of welding on Indian Railways",
            "d) The rail ends are moved to and fro"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The gas pressure welding method is simple but has not been adopted on large scale by the Indian Railways. The actual reason behind this is the irregularity in the availability of gas and limited output.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "What should be done to improve the loose sleepers and the disturbed track geometry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replace it with new ones",
            "b) Proper Maintenance",
            "c) Additional parts should be added",
            "d) Travel should not be permitted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Moving rails cause disturbance in the track geometry, effects alignment, gauge and other track components. Thus the track needs to be maintained which offers safe and comfortable journey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is false?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Life of track is independent of track maintenance",
            "b) Tightening a bolt or Hammering dog spikes is a part of track maintenance",
            "c) Maintenance saves money",
            "d) Neglecting track maintenance may render it unrepairable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Regular track maintenance helps in reducing operation costs and fuel consumption. Proper maintenance of track ensures lesser wear and tear of components and thus increases the life of track.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "What purpose does a Jim Crow serves in track maintenance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Removes kinks",
            "b) Removes rails",
            "c) For digging out ballast",
            "d) Squaring of sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For Through packing examination of rails, sleepers and fastenings is done. The defective sleepers are removed and loose fastenings are tightened. A Jim Crow is used to remove any kinks if present in the rail.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "How is gauge adjustment done in case of wooden sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) With keys",
            "b) Replacing the gauge components",
            "c) Realignment",
            "d) Refitting the dog spikes at a new location"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Wooden sleepers gauge adjustments should be avoided. This is because it can be done only by removing the dog spikes and refitting them at some other location. New holes are bored and spikes are re-driven.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Cotters are used for the gauge adjustment of which of the following types of sleeper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CST-9 sleepers",
            "b) Wooden sleepers",
            "c) Steel trough sleepers",
            "d) Concrete sleepers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gauge adjustment is case of CST-9 sleepers is done with the help of cotters. Gauge can be adjusted to a maximum extent of -3mm to +10mm. Keys are used in case of steel trough sleepers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "What is hogging of joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depression of rail ends at joints",
            "b) Depression of the middle part of the rail",
            "c) Corrosion of joints",
            "d) Staggering of rails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In hogging of joints, the two rail ends at the joint get depressed. This may be because of poor maintenance of joints, loose and faulty fastenings or other such reasons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "What should preferably be done to remove hogging if it occurs on a small scale?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cropping the hogged portion",
            "b) Dehogging machine",
            "c) Over packing of joint sleepers",
            "d) Replacing the whole rail"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If dehogging occurs on a small scale the fittings are tightened and the joint sleepers are over packed. Liners and shims can be used in removing the defect in case the fittings are loose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "What can happen if there is provision of wooden sleepers in a track that is normally laid with metal sleepers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hogging of rails",
            "b) Sagging of rails",
            "c) High joints",
            "d) Pumping joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Such discrepancies in the type of sleepers can result into High joints. This results in production of effect of camel back riding and makes the journey very uncomfortable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the following is correct in case of pumping joints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It pumps out mud and water",
            "b) It pumps out only mud",
            "c) It pumps out fine dust",
            "d) It occurs in dry season"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A joint which blows fine dust during passage of train is called blowing joints. In rainy seasons these joints pump mud and water and are known as pumping joints.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Which of the following activity must be done when the track undergoes regrading?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lifting of track",
            "b) Providing drainage facilities",
            "c) Replacing the joints",
            "d) Adjusting the creep"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the yard is remodelled or sag is developed due to defective maintenance lifting of track becomes necessary. A maximum of 75mm of track should be lifted at a time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "What can be done to remove the Centre bound sleeper defect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lifting of track",
            "b) Over packing of joints",
            "c) Loosening the ballast at ends",
            "d) Loosening the ballast at the centre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sometimes the sleeper starts to receive support at the centre instead of ends. This defect leads to rocking of trains and degrades quality of track. It can be removed by loosening the ballast at the centre of sleeper.\n"
    }
]